<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A loyal subiects looking-glasse, or A good subiects direction necessary and requisite for euery good Christian, liuing within any ciuill regiment or politique state, to view, behold, and examine himselfe in, that he may the better frame the course of his life, according to the true grounds of the duties of an honest and obedient subiect to his king, and to arme himselfe against all future syren songs, and alluring intisements of subtill, disloyall, dissembling, and vnnaturall conspirators, traitors, and rebels. Collected for the most part out of both olde and later writers, whose names are in the next page set downe. Wherevnto are brieflie added sixe speciall causes of vndutifull subiects disloyaltie. By William Willymat.</title>
            <author>Willymat, William, d. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120179</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855378</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15494)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1504:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A loyal subiects looking-glasse, or A good subiects direction necessary and requisite for euery good Christian, liuing within any ciuill regiment or politique state, to view, behold, and examine himselfe in, that he may the better frame the course of his life, according to the true grounds of the duties of an honest and obedient subiect to his king, and to arme himselfe against all future syren songs, and alluring intisements of subtill, disloyall, dissembling, and vnnaturall conspirators, traitors, and rebels. Collected for the most part out of both olde and later writers, whose names are in the next page set downe. Wherevnto are brieflie added sixe speciall causes of vndutifull subiects disloyaltie. By William Willymat.</title>
                  <author>Willymat, William, d. 1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Elde for Robert Boulton, and are to be sould at his shop at Chancerie lane end neere Holborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1604]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A variant of the edition dated 1604.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Cropped; some print faded.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20868:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20868:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LOYAL SVBIECTS LOOKING-GLASSE, Or A good ſubiects Direction, neceſſary and requiſite for euery good Chriſtian, liuing within any ciuill regiment or politique ſtate, to view, behold, and examine himſelfe in, that he may the better frame the courſe of his life, according to the true grounds of the duties of an honest and obedient ſubiect to his King, and to arme himſelfe againſt all future Syren ſongs, and alluring intiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſubtill, diſloyall, diſſembling, and vnnaturall conſpiraters, traitors, and rebels.</p>
            <p>Collected for the moſt part out of both olde and <hi>later writers, whoſe names are in the next</hi> page ſet downe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherevnto are brieflie added ſixe</hi> ſpeciall cauſes of vndutifull <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects diſloyaltie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM WILLYMAT.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Elde</hi> for <hi>Robert Boulton,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop at Chancerie lane end neere Holborne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors_consulted">
            <pb facs="tcp:20868:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The names of the Authors out of <hi>which this preſent Treatiſe hath for the</hi> moſt part beene collected.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Auguſtine.</item>
                     <item>Ambroſe.</item>
                     <item>Theophilacti.</item>
                     <item>Caluine.</item>
                     <item>Muſculus.</item>
                     <item>Marlorate.</item>
                     <item>Hyperius.</item>
                     <item>Hemingius.</item>
                     <item>Piſcator.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Iacobus Rex.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Bullinger.</item>
                     <item>Bucer.</item>
                     <item>Coruinus.</item>
                     <item>Luther.</item>
                     <item>Vrſinus.</item>
                     <item>M.H. Latimer.</item>
                     <item>Perkinſus.</item>
                     <item>Turnbull.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20868:2"/>
            <head>To the right vertuous, excellent, <hi>and most High and Noble Prince</hi> HENRIE, by the grace of God Prince of Wales, <hi>Duke of Cornewell, Earle of Cheſter, and heire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant</hi> to the Realmes of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE late gracious acceptance, most worthy yong Prince (with ſo prompt &amp; welwilling hand, ſo amiable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant a countenance, and ſo kinde and courteous words,) of thoſe mine haſtie and bold attempted labours, in tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into Latin and Engliſh verſe the ſeuerall Precepts and Inſtructions of our dread Soueraigne your Fathers Maieſties <hi>ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΟΝ ΔΩΡΟΝ,</hi> for your owne ſake, and vnto your owne ſelfe by him ſo Chriſtianly, fatherly, painfully and learnedly first penned: that <hi>Princes Looking-glaſſe,</hi> or Princes direction, (for that title or inſcription I then thought best befitting ſuch an argument) ſo benignly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, hath animated and encouraged me once againe, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh vnder your Graces Patrocinie, an other Looking-glaſſe, to wit, this preſent <hi>Loyall Subiects Looking-glaſſe,</hi> or a good ſubiects Direction, a treatiſe I ſuppoſe in theſe our laſt dayes and perillous times, very requiſite and neceſſarie for all Chriſtian ſubiects, like as was the other for a Chriſtian Prince. A fault I confeſſe is by me here committed, by this my ſecond ſo bold an enterpriſe, but yet <hi>Priùs perſpecta clementia, &amp; lenitate tua fretus,</hi> in good hope you will beare with my wants and imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and accept and reſpect mine heart, and plaine ſimple well
<pb facs="tcp:20868:3"/>meaning will, and rather poyſe the quantitie of mine affection and zeale to do good, (according to the gaine of that one poore talent that the Lord God hath committed vnto me,) then the qualitie of mine offence, I haue aduentur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d towards the helpe and inſtruction of the rude and ignorant ſort of ſubiects, who want both good bookes and good teachers, to publiſh this my ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Treatiſe befitting ſilly ſubiects, least through ignorance of their duties in true allegiance, they might the ſooner be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, deceiued, and withdrawne from giuing vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars.</hi> Simple and plaine indeed is this my worke, I must ſimply confeſſe, but yet an inſtrument of mine inward good affection, and a faithfull witneſſing meſſenger before both God and man, of my well-willing and well-meaning heart, <hi>Qui ſi non potui maxima parua dedi.</hi> And if your Grace (according to your former clemencie) ſhall happily vouchſafe it that good ſucceſſe as to come abroade to the view of the world vnder the wings of your benigne defence and fauourable protection, then I doubt not but of the better ſort it ſhall be the better accepted, and alſo from the nipping cancred Cater-pillers the more freely eſcape vntaunted, whoſe naturall inclination is rather to prie at the moates in other mens eyes, and to carpe and finde faults with other mens dooings, then to reſpect and perceiue beames in their owne eyes, or endeuour to profit Gods Church and their country with any their owne better labours. The euer-liuing God for his annointed Christ Ieſus his ſake, graunt you his eternall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, grace, and bleſſing, long and many happy yeares, with your owne hearts deſired felicitie, to the aduauncement of Gods honour and glory, to the ioye and comfort of all good faithfull Chriſtian hearts, to the terror of all your, and our forreigne enemies, and home-borne conſpirators, and to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie conuerſion or vtter confuſion of the publique and priuate aduerſaries of Gods eternall truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt loyall and dayly humble Orator: WILLIAM WILLYMAT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20868:3"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat, ſundrie, and manifold (good Chriſtian Reader) are the enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, inconueniences, and miſchiefs, which the lack of the right vſe of Gods moſt ſacred word, and the diligent care to be gouerned and ouer-ruled by the ſame, do bring, breede, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender among mortall men. O ſubtill ſerpent, ô deceiptfull and too diligent Sathan, euermore and euery where prying, ſeeking, and hunting like an hungrie and roaring Lyon for thy pray, when irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>Macheuillians</hi> apt ſchollers of that Italian hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound, deſperate careleſſe Atheiſts, obſtinate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling corner-creeping Papiſts, temporizing car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and verball Proteſtants, brainſick, heady, and male-contented Puritanes, and ſuch other like right borne children of this world, haue once caſt of the care, the knowledge, the vſe and practiſe of that true lightſome Lanterne of Gods word, which ſhould haue ſerued to guide their actions, and giuen light vnto their feete, whereby they might haue troden in the right pathes of all goodneſſe, how buſie, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and readie art thou then with thy legions of reprobate Angels, to ſtuffe and poſſeſſe, the blinde, ignorant, obſtinate, wilfull, rebellious, male-conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hearts, and buſie braines of ſuch men, with am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, enuie, malice, heart burning, diſcontentment of minde, murmurings and grudgings, diſlike and contempt of the moſt Chriſtian, and beſt gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as not fitting nor agreeing with their humors. ſlandering, euill ſpeaking, and back-biting, ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:20868:4"/>are in lawfull authoritie, conſpiracie, treaſon, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rebellion, and infinite other miſchiefes, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and too tedious here to recite. How true this is, as at ſundrie other times heretofore, ſo alſo now hath it proued it ſelfe by theſe laſt diſcoueries of ſome of our Engliſh diſloyall, vnnaturall and traiterous plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting practiſes and conſpiracies. The buildings, and very foundations whereof, the cloſe and cunning conueying whereof, yea though it were in the very fruite of a tree, the mightie Lord God our onely buckler, ſhield and ſure fortreſſe, according to his former accuſtomed goodneſſe and mercifull dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings (in our late Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raigne) hath vnto vs, reueiled, and detected, yea diſſipated, fruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, &amp; vtterly confounded, he for his holy names ſake worke in our hearts vnfeined thankfulneſſe for the ſame. Now for as much as God hath appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted admonitions and exhortations to encounter temptations, leaſt perhaps the deuill that old experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced and throughly practiſed enemie of mankind, the chiefeſt author of theſe and all other ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and abhominable attempts ſhould againe ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt and ingeſt the like lewde motions into the hearts of any mo, either forrein malignant ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or homeborne malitious, ambitious, and male-contented conſpirators. I haue here endeuoured my ſelfe to ſet forth for an admonition or warning before the eies of all ſuch as haue not conſented nor yeelded to any ſuch wicked and diuiliſh enterpriſes of treaſons and conſpiracies, this preſent treatiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>A loyall ſubiects Looking-glaſſe,</hi> or a good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects direction, wherein euery true hearted &amp; good
<pb facs="tcp:20868:4"/>meaning, yea and euery wauering minded, vnſtable and ſimple ignorant ſubiect may behold, ſee, and learne how to behaue himſelfe, and dutifully to liue vnder the gouernment of higher powers, whether they be ſupreame Magiſtrates, Emperours, Kings and Princes, or elſe inferior ſubordinate magiſtrates and officers, adhibited by the higher powers to the adminiſtration of things for the gouernment of the common-wealth. Herein I haue laboured to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes and hearts of all ſorts of ſubiects, what duties they owe, and are bounden by the plaine and expreſſe word of God, to performe to their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, of what degree or place ſo euer: A treatiſe I ſuppoſe very requiſite and neceſſary for theſe our enuious, malicious, ambitious, ſelf-louing, ſelf-wilie proud and rebellious dayes. Thoſe good &amp; learned authors both olde and of later times, whom I haue principally leaned vnto as my chiefe guids, directors and good maiſters, in the penning of this preſent <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> yee may ſee ſet downe by their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall names before the epiſtle dedicatory. I haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in followed the maner of thoſe Cookes which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into Gardens to gather herbes, caſt their eyes round about them, and looke vpon all, and crop and take but thoſe only which are moſt conuenient and needfull for their vſe and purpoſe at that time: Likewiſe haue I choſen &amp; excerpted out of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named writers, but thoſe things only which I thought would ſerue beſt, and moſt conueniently befit this preſent matter and time, and them for the helpe of the memorie of the readers, and for the readie finding out, and ſpeedy turning vnto any ſeuerall
<pb facs="tcp:20868:5"/>point or matter herein entreated of, I haue digeſted into ſeuerall chapters, according vnto the ſeuerall duties which are due vnto Magiſtrates ſet in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. I am not aſhamed to yeeld and plainly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that I haue collected this preſent treatiſe, for the moſt part thereof (though not all) out of the drift, ſence and meaning, yea and now and then the very words of other mens writings, for I deeme it a ſounder, a ſurer, and a ſafer courſe, to walke in the pathes and tread in the ſteps of former learned and allowed writers, that ſo I might alwayes haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient authoritie for mine opinions and allegations, then to range at randon in writing, and ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broach mine owne inuentions, ſeeing that, <hi>Nihiliam dici poteſt quod non ſit dictum prius.</hi> I weigh not, and I paſſe not for the virulent and malicious cauils, of neuer pleaſed <hi>Momus</hi>-like enuious back-biters, ſo that by my labours I may do any good, or be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to helpe to auoide any euill in this Church and common-wealth wherein I liue: which happie ſucceſſe that this my preſent treatiſe may haue, I pray thee gentle reader helpe me with thy zealous prayers to the Almightie, the onely giuer of all good gifts, to whom only be all worthy honor, praiſe and dominion for euer and euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20868:5"/>
            <head>The chiefe and principall matters contained in the firſt ſixe chapters of this Booke following.</head>
            <list>
               <head>In the first Chapter is conteined.</head>
               <item>WHat Emperours, Kings, Princes, &amp;c. are: by whom they were and are ordeined, and wherefore. page 3. &amp; 4.</item>
               <item>Of and from whom tyrants and euill Kings and Princes are: and wherefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſuch are exalted. pag. 4.</item>
               <item>Obedience the firſt thing due vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> belongeth vnto all higher powers, kings and principalities, yea although tyrannicall and euill gouernours. pag. 56.</item>
               <item>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>guments &amp; reaſons to perſwade vnto obedience to magiſtrats. Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Magiſtrates called Gods. idem.</item>
               <item>Of the defermities, and vglineſſe of rebellion, thereby to diſſwade from the ſame. 6.</item>
               <item>The horrible finnes &amp; miſchiefes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t range &amp; raigne in rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Commodities of obedience and peace. 7.</item>
               <item>To what end good examples of obedience do chieflie ſerue. 8.</item>
               <item>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is chieflie to be made by the examples of euill and rebellious ſubiects. idem.</item>
               <item>Examples of two of the beſt and moſt obedient faithfull ſubiects, moſt worthy to be imitated. 8. 9. 10.</item>
               <item>Example of <hi>Dauids</hi> behauiour towards king <hi>Saul,</hi> what it doth teach 9.</item>
               <item>A queſtion concerning obedience reſoluen. 11.</item>
               <item>What it is or a ſubiect to foſter and cheriſh an euill thought in his heart againſt his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueraigne. 12.</item>
               <item>What is to be done when a man is entiſed or drawne by any kinde of meanes to yeeld to treaſon. 14.</item>
               <item>Treaſon and treacherous plottings, and practiſes are not to be hid nor conceiled for any mans ſake whoſoeuer he be. idem.</item>
               <item>Delay is dangerous in hiding fire or treaſon. 15.</item>
               <item>Examples of <hi>Abſolon</hi> and of diuers other traito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and of their bad ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and confuſion. 15. 16. 17.</item>
               <item>Learne to take warning by other mens falles. 18.</item>
               <item>Diuers manners of puniſhments of traitors &amp; diſloyall ſubiects. 18. 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian</hi> his bridle againſt going on and continuing in ſinnes. 20</item>
               <item>The laſt argument or reaſon to mooue to obedience, drawne from Beaſts, Birdes, Fiſhes, &amp;c. 21.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the ſecond Chapter is conteined.</head>
               <item>HOw neceſſarie and profitable a thing feare is. pag. 22.</item>
               <item>To feare the king, commanded in holy Scriptures. idem.</item>
               <item>Two kinds of feare. 23.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:20868:6"/>
               <item>The profies of good feare. pag. 23.</item>
               <item>The nature of the good and child-like feare, explicated by two apte ſimilitudes. 24.</item>
               <item>The vertues or effects of the good feare, expreſſed by the effects of the feare of a Scholler towards his Scholemaiſter. Idem.</item>
               <item>Diuers &amp; ſundry effects of feare of a ſubiect towards his ſoueraine. ide.</item>
               <item>Hovv prinate men are to behaue themſelues tovvards ſuch as be in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, though they be neuer ſo bad and euill diſpoſed. 26</item>
               <item>Feare, though it be a very neceſſarie thing to be yeelded vnto the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er povvers and Magiſtrats, yet may it be abuſed: and of the firſt abuſe of this feare. 28.</item>
               <item>Of the ſecond kinde of feare. 29.</item>
               <item>The vſe and profit of ſeruile feare. 30.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the third Chapter is conteined.</head>
               <item>HOnour, the third thing belonging to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what it ſignifieth. 31.</item>
               <item>The actions of honouring are manifold, and wherein they doe conſiſt. ibidem.</item>
               <item>The firſt kind of honour due to Magiſtrates. ibidem.</item>
               <item>The ſecond kinde of honour due to Magiſtrates. 32.</item>
               <item>The third honour due to ſuperiours. ibid.</item>
               <item>The fourth honour due to ſuperiours. ibid.</item>
               <item>The beginnings of all conſpiracies, &amp;c. ariſe for the moſt part from the heart, that beginneth to fall away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honoring the higher powers. 33</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the fourth Chapter is conteined.</head>
               <item>PRayer the fourth thing belonging to <hi>Caeſar</hi> commaunding ſubiects in holy ſeriptures. page 33.</item>
               <item>What things eſpecially are to be prayed for in the behalfe of kings, Princes, &amp;c. 34.</item>
               <item>What kinde of kings &amp; rulers God commanded to be praied for. ibid.</item>
               <item>What it is not to pray for kings, &amp;c. 35.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the fift Chapter is conteined.</head>
               <item>TRibute, taxes, ſubſidies, and other ſuch like royall cuſtomes, the ſift thing due vnto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> 36.</item>
               <item>The cauſes for which ſubſidies, taxes, &amp;c. are greeuous and odious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the common people. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Tributes, ſubfidies, taxes, &amp;c. amongſt all nations of old, haue beene vſually payed, and wherefore. 37.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theophilactus</hi> and <hi>Bucer</hi> their opinions for paiment of tribute, taxes, &amp;c. 38.</item>
               <item>The onely helpe and lawfull remedie for not paiment of Subſedies, taxes, &amp;c. ibidem.</item>
               <item>Diuers cauſes wherefore tribute, ſubſedies, taxes, &amp;c. are to be paid. 39.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:20868:6"/>
               <item>Diuers great benefits and bleſſings which ſubiects receiue by their kings, rulers, &amp;c. 40.</item>
               <item>Hovv kings may both take and employ tributes, taxes, ſubſedies, and ſuch like cuſtomes. 41.</item>
               <item>Leſſons neceſſary for kings, Princes, &amp;c. to obſerue, note, and practiſe concerning the exacting of impoſitions, taxes, &amp;c. ibid.</item>
               <item>Leſſons neceſſary for the common people and ſubiects to obſerue, note, and practiſe, concerning their behauiour and conceits againſt kings, Princes, &amp;c. for lifting and demanding of ſubſedies, taxes, &amp;c. ibid.</item>
               <item>A neceſſary queſtion concerning ſuch ſubiects as being of vvealth and ſubſtance, will ſeeke and practiſe falſe and lying ſhifts and euaſions, to eſcape, or to diminiſh their right and due paiments of taxes, ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, &amp;c. partly by defrauding the king, and partly by oppreſſing and vvringing their poore neighbours: and the anſvver therevnto. 41.42.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Martin Luther</hi> his opinion concerning the ſubiects dutie, if kings, princes, &amp;c. ſhall happen to impoſe and exact any greeuous &amp; ouerchargeable taxes, ſubſedies, or other cuſtomes &amp; paiments 43.</item>
               <item>And alſo S <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his opinion, and likevviſe king <hi>Iames</hi> his opinion in the ſame caſe. 45.</item>
               <item>Of mutuall loue and agreement betvveene Prince and people, and of the good thereof. 46.</item>
               <item>King <hi>James</hi> his Maieſties moſt louing, Chriſtian and excellent coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile to his ſonne Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> concerning lifting of ſubſedies, &amp;c. ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the ſixt Chapter is conteined,</head>
               <item>PRiuate men may not intermeddle nor take vpon them the office of a Magiſtrate vvithout ſome lavvfull calling therevnto. pag. 47.</item>
               <item>The people of euery kngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, countrie, or city, deuided into 3. ſorts. ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>Two things eſpecially to be conſidered in the ſixt dutie of ſubiects vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> 48.</item>
               <item>The reuenge of any iniurie to vvhom it properlie belongeth. idem.</item>
               <item>The ſixe cauſes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſſe of ſubiect; added and briefly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of, in the end of this loyall ſubiects Looking-glaſſe.
<list>
                     <item>1 Pride.</item>
                     <item>2 Ambition.</item>
                     <item>3 Enuie.</item>
                     <item>4 Lack of vviſdome and knovvledge.</item>
                     <item>5 Diſcontentment of minde.</item>
                     <item>6 Miſliking and inueighing againſt the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of malefactors.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <lg>
               <head>The aforeſaid ſixe cauſes of ſubiects vndutifulneſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe vi. verſes following.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>The cauſe vvhy ſubiects duties faile, vvho liſts to haue deſcride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let him giue eare, and marke a vvhile, the first cauſe it is Pride:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſecond is Ambition: Enuie the third place vvill haue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fourth is vvant of knovvledge ſure, &amp; vvant of vviſdome graue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fift cauſe vvho deſires to knovv, is minds diſcontentment,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſixt is the vniust diſlike of levvd mens puniſhment.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:20868:7"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> contained in the 6. cauſes <hi>of ſubiects vndutifulnes, added in the end of this treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>AS Sathan of a glorious Angell, through Pride became anvglie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, forſaking his loyaltie to God, ſo the ſame Sathan by the ſame pride, dayly tempteth man to fall avvay from loyaltie to higher powers ordeined of God for mans good. pag. 50.</item>
               <item>Pride wherein it conſiſteth idem.</item>
               <item>Honourable houres and great men in the vvorld, through pride haue wrought their owne vtter confuſion. 51.</item>
               <item>The deuils craft and ſubtiltie to inſnare men through pride, &amp; to bring them thereby to treaſon, conſpiracie and rebellion. ibid.</item>
               <item>Of Ambition the ſecond cauſe of the vndutifulneſſe of ſubiects, &amp; here what ambition is, and who are ſaid and noted to be ambition. 52.</item>
               <item>Notable examples of ambitious mens filles and of the manifold moſt notorious miſchiefes and inconueniences that many haue fallen into through ambition. 54.</item>
               <item>Of Enuie the third cauſe of ſubiects vndutifulneſſe: from whence En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſpringeth, and of the fruites thereof. 55.</item>
               <item>Diuers ſimilitudes deſcribing the nature of Enuie. ibid.</item>
               <item>None neuer ſo vertuous eſcape the virulent and ſianderous nippings of the enuious crue. 56.</item>
               <item>Of want of wiſedome and knovvledge, the fourth cauſe of ſubiects vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſſe. 58.</item>
               <item>The great inconueniences that fall out through want of wiſedom and knowledge in vndiſcreet ſubiects. idem.</item>
               <item>Princes purpoſes, pollicies &amp; proceedings, not yet publiſhed &amp; knowne abroade, are not to be condemned and miſconſtrued. 58.</item>
               <item>Of diſcontentedneſſe of minde, the fift cauſe of ſubiects vndutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. 60.</item>
               <item>Two ſortes of ſubiects eſpecially troubled with diſcontentment of minde, &amp;c. idem.</item>
               <item>The wicked nature and vngodly, vndurifull and diſloyall poſitions, and euill corrupting words of deſperate godleſſe Athriſts, prodigall ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, and royſting caualliers, bewraying their contempt of God, and vndutifulneſſe to higher powers and magiſtracie 60 &amp; 61.</item>
               <item>Counſaile and directions for vnthrifts and waſt ales to take another courſe. 62.</item>
               <item>Miſliking of due &amp; deſerued puniſhment of malefactors, the ſixt cauſe of the vndutifulneſſe of ſubiects, and of their errortherein. idem.</item>
               <item>Aduiſe, counſaile, and neceſſarie directions for buſie miſlikers and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreete inueighers, againſt the puniſhment of euill doers, &amp;c. 63.64.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20868:7"/>
            <head>A loyall Subiects Looking-glaſſe.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Moſt Chriſtian King, a moſt ſincere profeſſor,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>J Rex.</hi> in his treatiſe of the true law of free Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies.</note> and defender of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall truth, yet at this day liuing, (and maugre the heads of the moſt ſubtill ſuggeſting ſerpent, and all his wicked, traiterous, and rebellious imps, long may he liue) hath written, that <hi>next the knowledge of God, the right knowledge of ſubiects alleageance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the forme of gouernment eſtabliſhed among them, is a thing moſt neceſſarie to be knowne.</hi> The ignorance hereof,
<note place="margin">The effects of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or contempt of the right knowledge of ſubiects alledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> or (that which is worſſe) the retchleſſe and wilfull contempt hereof hath bread the heauie calamities, the endleſſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the moſt miſerable wreacke and ouerthrow of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie flouriſhing common-wealths, and alſo the worthily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued fall and confuſion of the ſtate, lands, goods, lifes and bloud of many diſloyall, infatuated, maliciouſly giuen, male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, ambitious, traiterous conſpiratours, and rebels, in many heretofore flouriſhing common-wealths, kingdomes, and monarchies. Examples hereof, and that diuers within the kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> are yet greener, freſher, and more common, both in the hearts and mouthes of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands yet huing, who haue beene both eyed and eared wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the ſame, then that they can caſilie be forgotten. Leaſt therefore any other ſubiects now liuing,
<note place="margin">The ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cauſes that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to write this preſent treatiſe.</note> or their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, or any other generation yet vnborne, ſhould be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after trapped in the like ſnares, and ſo become ſubiect to the like confuſions, (the naturall zeale that I beare to my natiue countrie, and the great griefe I haue to heare and ſee my poore country-men, either ſo ignorant, or ſo careleſſe of true loyall ſubiects duties, me there vnto ſpeciall moouing) I haue heere done mine endeuoure to ſet downe in this preſent treatiſe, the true grounds of the moſt ſpeciall duties, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20868:8"/>naturall ſubiectes are found to performe to higher powers, whether they be ſupreame Maieſtrates,
<note place="margin">Magiſtrats and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours are of tvvo ſorts.</note> as Emperors, Kings, and Princes, Gods owne lieutenaunts, vicegerents, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, or whether they be their ſubordinate magiſtrates and inferior officers, which alſo in their degrees and places are the ordinance of God, for the good gouernment of men, that vnder them they might lead a quiet and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie.</p>
               <p>The grounds of this preſent treatiſe, or <hi>Loyall ſubiects loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſe</hi> (for ſo not incongruently I haue entituled it in the beginning) I purpoſe through Gods aſſiſtance to draw out of the words of Chriſt Ieſus his owne mouth,
<note place="margin">From vvhence the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe are drawne.</note> which I haue thought not impertinent here to inſert. <hi>Giue vnto Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar the things which are Caeſars.</hi> By the which word <hi>Caeſar,</hi> (for ſo were the Romane Emperours called, like as the Kings of Egypt were alwayes called <hi>Pharaos</hi>) is not onely to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the perſon of the Emperour <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> then raigning and ruling,
<note place="margin">What is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded by the vvord <hi>Caeſar.</hi> The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts then neuer learned of Chriſt to diſalovve Magiſtracy.</note> but alſo euery other Emperour, King, Prince, and ciuill Magiſtrate, temporall ruler, worldly gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or officer whatſoeuer. Moreouer by theſe words of our Sauiour Chriſt, it is further to be vnderſtanded and learned, that he miſliked not, nor condemned, but approoued, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confirmed all ciuill regiment, politique ſtate, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with all things that to it appertaine.</p>
               <p>Now for the things which are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> that is for all duties which ſubiects doe owe and ought to performe to all their ſuperiour gouernours and magiſtrates, that is the matter which I haue here ſpecially to deale with, that is the marke which I haue chieflie to ſhoote at, and thoſe things by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent reading, ſearching, and obſeruing of learned authors, both diuine and prophane, I finde to be eſpedially fixe, to wit:
<list>
                     <item>1.
<note place="margin">Sixe things eſpecially due vnto <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                        </note> Obedience.</item>
                     <item>2. Feare.</item>
                     <item>3. Honor.</item>
                     <item>4. Prayer.</item>
                     <item>5. Tribute, taxes, ſubſidies, &amp;c.</item>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20868:8"/>
                     <item>6. Not raſhlie to take in hand (or intermeddle) with any part of Magiſtrates office without a lawfull calling.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſaid ſixe duties of ſubiects due vnto their <hi>Caeſar,</hi> I haue comprehended in theſe verſes following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sixe things by right are vnto</hi> Caeſar <hi>due,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1. <hi>Obedience firſt vnto his iuſt decrees,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Next feare inſixt in hearts of ſubiects true,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The third is honour due from all degrees,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The fourth for happie ſtate of Prince to pray, That God with peace may ſtill his life prolong:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>And fifthy tribute willingly to paye, Whereby his wealth may daily growe more ſtrong,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>The ſixe that none preſume for glories ſake, Vuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lde the parts of Magiſtrates to take.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Obedience, the firſt dutie of a loyall ſubiect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Emperours, Kings, Princes, and other ſupreame Powers, and Magiſtrats, of what names or titles ſo euer, according to the faſhions and cuſtome of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and languages, that dwell in all the world, are Gods Vizeroyes, Vizegerents Lieutenants and Deputies here on earth, and all ſubordinate and inferiour Maieſtrates and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, hauing their commiſſion out of their principall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, though but <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> at the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the higher power,
<note place="margin">Wherefore magiſtrates vvere or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</note> yet for their time they are alſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and appointed of God: All ſuch both ſupreme and inferiour ciuill magiſtrates are miniſters armed both with lawes and ſword, to be nurſers to Gods Church or people, and Fathers to the common-wealth, to guide, gouerne and order the people within their ſeuerall circuites and charges, whoſe hearts are in the Lords hands, and the Lords ſword in their hands, to execute iuſtice and diſcipline, as well in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20868:9"/>as in all other cauſes, for the benefit and good of the good and the puniſhment of the bad. Theſe are exalted and enthroned onely by the will and ordinance of God:
<note place="margin">By whom the higher povvers are ordeined. <hi>Prou.</hi> 8.15. <hi>VViſ.</hi> 6.23.</note> So God himſelfe proteſteth ſaying: <hi>By me Kings raigne, and Princes decree iuſtice.</hi> So doth the Wiſemen tell and teach: <hi>Giue eare yee that rule the multitudes, and glorie in the multitude of the people, for the rule is giuen you of the Lord, and power by the moſt high: Wiſd.</hi> 6.23. So the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh of God ſaying:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.25.</note> 
                  <hi>He taketh away Kings, and ſetteth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Kings.</hi> Yea more cleare is it then light it ſelfe, that not onely good Emperours Kings, and Princes, are of God: but alſo very ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and the worſt Kings, and Princes, be they neuer ſo great an euill, be they neuer ſo great a plague to their owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, or to their neighbour nations.</p>
               <p>Good Kings are giuen of God in his great mercie,
<note place="margin">Tytants &amp; bad Kings are alſo ſet vp and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined of God, and wherefore.</note> and euill Kings in his wrath and iuſtice: for the finnes of the people he giueth an euill king in his anger, <hi>Hoſeas. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 3.11.</hi> for the ſinnes of the people he ſuffereth an hypocrite to raigne, <hi>Iob. 34.30.</hi> Euill Princes are the inſtruments of Gods iuſtice, and the executioners of his vengeance, as their very titles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, for ſo was <hi>Aſhur</hi> called the <hi>Rod of Gods wrath, Eſa. 10.5.</hi> So was <hi>Nabuchodonozar</hi> King of <hi>Babel</hi> called <hi>Gods Seruant, Ierem. 27.6.</hi> So did <hi>Attyla</hi> that moſt valiant <hi>Scythian</hi> Prince, conquerour of diuerſe countries, kingdomes and nations, call himſelfe <hi>Flagellum Dei;</hi> the Scourge of God. So was <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> that cruell tyrant King of <hi>Parthia</hi> called <hi>Ira Dei</hi> and <hi>Terror orbis;</hi> the wrath of God, and the terrour of the world. Vnto theſe and all ſuch like were they good or bad, among diuers other duties doth God himſelfe appoint and commaund euery Chriſtian ſubiect,
<note place="margin">Obedience due vnto bad kings.</note> of what ranck or degree ſo euer to yeelde obedience. This is one of thoſe things which our Sauiour Chriſt ſpake of, when he ſaid, <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> Thus ſaith his choſen veſſell <hi>S. Paul; Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, and the powers that be ordeined of God, Rom.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1.</note> 13.</hi> Alſo he writeth vnto <hi>Titus</hi> after this manner; <hi>Put them in remembrance that they be ſubiect vnto Principalities and powers, and that they be obedient, &amp;c. Tit. 3.1.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20868:9"/>taught by the ſame ſpirit, ſaith; <hi>Submit your ſelues vnto all maner ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as to the ſuperiour, or vnto Gouernours, as vnto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of euill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well: for it is the will of God that by well dooing yee may put to ſilence the ignorance of the fooliſh men. 1. Pet. 2.13.14.15.</hi> Diuers and ſundrie are the reaſons and cauſes which ſhould mooue and ſtirre vp Chriſtian loyall ſubiects to this dutie of obedience,
<note place="margin">Three ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or reaſons to perſwade to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> whereof the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the before noted place, <hi>Rom. 13.</hi> vſeth three ſeuerall arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade therevnto. The firſt drawne from the excellencie or worthineſſe of the firſt author or ordeiner of Magiſtrates, which was God himſelfe; and therefore whatſoeuer God himſelfe firſt inſtituted, ordeined and founded, that is moſt worthy to be embraced, receiued, regarded and obayed. The ſecond reaſon he there vſeth, is taken from the penaltie and puniſhment that followeth ſuch as neglect, reiect, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne this obedience to the higher powers, and that is iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is not onely the iudgement of earthly iudges, but alſo the vengeance of God for their reſiſtance &amp; rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt Gods ordinance. The third argument is alſo drawne from the end; for which Magiſtrates were ordeined and ſet vp by God, which is for the praiſe and good of ſuch as doe well, but on the otherſide to terrifie and take venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on ſuch as doe euill, for the ſword is not put into their hands for naught, or to doe nothing therewith.
<note place="margin">Tvvo argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or reaſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o perſvvade to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: out of 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Two of the very ſame reaſons to induce and perſwade to this dutifull obedience vſeth the ſaid <hi>S. Peter</hi> in the before alledged place. <hi>1. Pet. 2.13.</hi> Moreouer to mooue ſubiects the more readily and willingly to yeeld obedience vnto theſe higher powers, God hath adorned and beautified the ſtate &amp; perſons of Magiſtrates, with moſt honorable titles, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending vnto men the dignitie thereof, in that he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaueth them ſometimes his owne name and ſtile, as in <hi>Pſalm.
<note place="margin">Magiſtrats called gods a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.6. and wherefore.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>26. I haue ſaid yee are Gods.</hi> Whence we ſee then, that men placed in authoritie are called Gods, becauſe they repreſent his Maieſtie in ruling and gouerning his people, this is a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20868:10"/>of no ſmall importance to worke obedience to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in Gods people, if ſo be that they be of God indeede. God ſo honoureth rulers and gouernours, that in token ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he inueſteth them with his owne name, to teach their ſubiects that they ſhould obay them as they would do him, to whom that name doth of beſt right belong.</p>
               <p>To ſtirre vp and drawe on good ſubiects the more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and willingly to obedience, let them view and behold, yea though it be but a little and a farre off,
<note place="margin">Of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities &amp; vglineſſe of rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto it is likened.</note> the deformities and ouglineſſe of rebellion, and the hainouſneſſe of diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, which may not vnaptly be called <hi>Monſtrum horrendum, informe, ingens, cui lumen ademptum;</hi> An horrible, great, blind, and an ill fauoured monſter: which not vnfitly reſembleth that confuſed <hi>Chaos</hi> ſpoken of by <hi>Heſiodus</hi> the <hi>Greeke</hi> Poet, and deſcribed by <hi>Ouid</hi> to be <hi>Congeſtaeôdem non bene iuncta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſcordia ſemina rerum:</hi> or moſt fitly it reſembleth euen hell it ſelfe;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. lib. ſer. ſermon.</hi> 26.</note> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> writeth of it, to be a place <hi>Plenus ardore incomparabili, plenus ſaetore intollerabili, plenus dolore innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merabili, vbi tenebrae, vbi horror aeternus, vbi nullus ordo, vbi omnis miſeria.</hi> So that <hi>Tuchydides</hi> the <hi>Greeke</hi> Hiſtorigrapher writeth full truely of it,
<note place="margin">E. N.</note> that <hi>Rebellion is all kinde of euill.</hi> And as truly ſaith a later writer of it; that <hi>Rebellion is not onely a ſinne, but euen the ſincke of all ſinne;</hi> for herein lurketh the puddle of all filthie ſinnes whatſoeuer, againſt God &amp; man, againſt Gods andointed Vizegerents, Deputies and Lieutenants, againſt countrie and countrimen, againſt parents, children, kinsfolks, and friends.
<note place="margin">In rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is open and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt periury.</note> In rebellion is apparant periurie, whereby Gods holy name is contemned and diſhonoured, by breaking of oathes, and renouncing alleagiance before ſworne to lawfull Kings and Princes, by calling to witneſſe the name and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God.
<note place="margin">In rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſwearing and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie.</note> In rebellion moſt wicked, deteſtable, vaine ſwearing and blaſpheming of Gods holy name, and of the parts &amp; members of the bleſſed body of Chriſt Ieſus, breake out without either feare of God or any controulment of lawes.
<note place="margin">In rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sabboth.</note> In rebellion you ſhall ſee the Lords day neglected, vnhallowed, and the reuerent vſe thereof prophaned, not onely by the rebels themſelues, but alſo by thoſe Chriſtians
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20868:10"/>that would full gladly and withall their hearts keepe it holy, and yet hereby are forced to aſſemble and meete armed in the field, to ſaue themſelues, their goods, houſes, wiues and children againſt the inuaſion and furie of rebels.
<note place="margin">In rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are thefts, murthers, robbing &amp; ſpoiling, whordom, rauiſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of widows, wiue, and maides, &amp;c.</note> Moſt er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant thefts, deſperate robberies, and moſt cruell murthers, with ſpoiling and bloud-ſhedding violence, not againſt a fewe, but whole and infinite multitudes, do then moſt range, when rebellion beareth the ſwaye. Damnable whoredomes, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, fornication, ſorcible rapes and rauiſhments, violating and deflowring of matrons, widdowes, mens wines, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, virgins and maides, are moſt rife in time of rebellion among moſt horrible and damnable rebels. And finally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe moſt impious &amp; atheiſticall rebels,
<note place="margin">In rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the breach and contempt of both Gods laws and mans lavves.</note> are all lawes both diuine and humaine, broken, contemned, and trampled vnder foote, and all manner of ſinnes poſſible to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt God and man are ſet abroache. Who then is ſo blind but he may euen with halfe an eye, ſee and eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the wonderfull difference betweene this beaſtly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne, this terrible monſter of rebellion, inſurrection, diſloyaltie and diſobedience to higher powers, and the moſt excellent, ſweete, amiable, and moſt pretious guift of God, bleſſed Peace, the daughter of Chriſtian, faithfull, and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience. For by the one, namely rebellion, ſhall men reape ſuch vnſauorie, ſuch infected and poyſoned fruites, as you here before haue read or heard of: By the other, to wit,
<note place="margin">Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of peace and obedience.</note> Peaceable obedience ſhall good loyall ſubiects <hi>dwell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, euery man vnder his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, and vnder his Figge tree, from Dan vnto Berſheba:</hi> from <hi>Portſmouth</hi> in the South parts of <hi>England,</hi> to <hi>Dungisbie</hi> in the North parts of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſo through out the vtmoſt parts of all good King <hi>Iames</hi> his fortunate kingdomes and dominions. How fooliſh, how be witched, and how inſatiated are then thoſe ſubiects, that will not lay hold on, follow and imbrace this ſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, neceſſary, profitable, dutifull and loyall obedience,
<note place="margin">Ambabus vel vtriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> and that <hi>obuijs vlnis &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (<hi>quod aiunt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.)</p>
               <p>To perſwade and allure ſubiects to dutifull obedience, both holy Scriptures and diuers learned prophane writers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20868:11"/>haue ſundrie examples, moſt manifeſtly ſetting before mens eies,
<note place="margin">To what end good examples of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doe chieflie ſerue. What vſe to make of the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient &amp; rebellious ſubiects.</note> and conſideration of their hearts, both how the beſt ſort of ſubiects haue in this caſe of obedience behaued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, (whoſe examples in this tempeſtuous and bluſtering world may ſerue as they were anckers or ſtaues to ſtay, and as it were firmely to ſtabliſh wauering minded ſubiects by) and alſo examples of the worſt ſort of ſubiects, wheſe ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious aſpiring mindes, and enuious rebelling heads haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured both their owne and their poſterities moſt miſerable ruine and vtter ouerthrowe, that ſuch like affected ſubiects as they were, might by their precedent falles, learne in time, and beware, and ſtoppe the beginnings of all diſobedient, rebellious and ſeditious practiſes.</p>
               <p>For the better ſort of ſubiects,
<note place="margin">Tvvo of the beſt examples of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</note> let <hi>Dauid</hi> his behauiour whiles he was yet a ſubiect, out of the olde Teſtament: and <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> his behauiour, when he yet in his manhood wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred for a time, and conuerſed with vs here on earth, out of the new Teſtament be ſet before our eyes to view and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of, for our learning and inſtruction, in the ſteed &amp; name of all the reſt, as moſt fitte and liuely paternes for all good, loyall, and true hearted ſubiects, to ſhape, faſhion and frame their duties by: whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> when God had deliuered his bitter perſecuting enemie King <hi>Saul</hi> into his hands in a Caue where <hi>Dauid</hi> and his men had hid themſelues from the preſence of <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4.5.6.</note> when and where <hi>Dauid</hi> wanted neither fit occaſions nor exaſperating counſaile to haue kild his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatie the King, being ſo neare him that he had cut off the lap of his garment, yet he abſtained from ſo vndutifull a fact, praying the Lord to keepe him from doing any ſuch thing vnto his maiſter the Lords annoynted, and with earneſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie ouercame his ſeruants that they ſhould not ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 26</note> The like alſo fell out an other time not long after, when <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> entred King <hi>Sauls</hi> camp, both the King himſelfe and all his hoaſt being caſt on a deepe ſleepe, and came ſo neare the kings body, that <hi>Abiſhai</hi> carneſtly prayed <hi>Dauid</hi> to giue him leaue to ſmite the king with his owne ſpeare, affirming that he would lay it on ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20868:11"/>ſoundly, that one ſtroake ſhould ſerue to make him ſure for euer, yet <hi>Dauid</hi> would not conſent vnto this,
<note place="margin">Learne of <hi>Dauid</hi> not to yeeld to bad coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſeeme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo good and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie.</note> but prayed the Lords as before to keepe him from laying his hands on the Lords annoynted. Many examples before this had <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhewed of his prompt and ready obedience to his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord and maiſter King <hi>Saul;</hi> yea euen to the often hazerding of his bloud and life againſt the Kings enemies the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> as the bookes of <hi>Samuel</hi> in diuers chapters do teſtifie. And here now in theſe two examples of ſparing the Kings life, being ſo ſtraunglie deliuered into his hands, he ſetteth forth a generall rule and leſſon for all ſubiects in the world among all poſterities,
<note place="margin">What <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth teach.</note> not in any wiſe to reſiſt higher powers, nor by their owne priuate authoritie to take the ſword in hand, nor to conſent to the taking of the ſword in hand, to kill or hurt any King or other ſupreme ruler and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, no not although it lye in their power neuer ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, without any bloud ſhedding, tumults, or great broyles to effect the ſame.</p>
               <p>This good ſubiect <hi>Dauid</hi> was ſo louing and kinde, yea euen vnto a bad King his vndeſerued enemie, and euery where hunting after, and thirſting for his innocent bloud, that at the very laſt caſt of King <hi>Saul,</hi> when an <hi>Amalekite</hi> by his conſent and requeſt had ſlaine him, and brought the firſt tidings thereof to <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſuppoſing to haue receiued ſome great reward at <hi>Dauids</hi> hands for his newes, vpon the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge there of <hi>Dauid</hi> after he had a while mourned and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> he asked the meſſenger whether he were not affraide to laye hands on the Lords annoynted to deſtroy him; and preſently commanded one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to kill him for that act by his owne mouth confeſſed. O <hi>Dauid, Dauid,</hi> thou moſt worthy mirrour of obedience and dutifulneſſe to Gods ſubſtitutes here on earth; what if thou were aliue in theſe our dayes? Thou that didſt ſo readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie obay, ſo reuerently vſe, ſo paciently forbeare, ſo ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully mourne and weepe for the death, and ſo willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge the death of a wicked King, that had beene ſo diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to God, and whom God had therefore vtterly caſt off,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20868:12"/>with what reproachfull termes and irefull words wouldſt thou not exclaime vpon, and reuile, yea with what tortures and torments of moſt ſhamefull death wouldſt thou not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, ſuch forlorne diueliſh bloudie hel-hounds, ſuch deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate treacherous conſpiratours, and viperous rebels, as moſt naughtilie, vnkindly, and vnnaturally againſt Gods Church, their natiue countrie, the Kings Maieſties perſon and eſtate, will attempt to hazard the liues of ſo many thouſands of men, women, and children, by depoſing or murthering ſo kinde, naturall, and louing a King, as is now our moſt noble Soueraigne Lord King IAMES,
<note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King <hi>Iames,</hi> and his lurking aduerſaries.</note> ſo gratious a King, ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and prouident for the good and welfare euen of his worſt ſubiects, ſuch a mainteiner of bleſſed peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not only at home, but alſo with forraine nations, and neighbour countries round about, ſuch a fauourer of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie and learning, ſuch a <hi>Mecoenas</hi> of the learned, moſt bountifull to all goodmen, yea though to his owne priuate loſſe, hinderance and charges, and ſo neceſſarie a head for the whole body and ſtate of all his realmes kingdomes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions? Let this one notable example of <hi>Dauid</hi> that good and obedient ſubiect ſerue in this place for all other out of the old Teſtament. Out of the new Teſtament what more excellent and worthy example can be produced to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered or meditated vpon,
<note place="margin">The moſt vvorthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21 <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.17 <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.25 <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> and carefully to be imitated of all good Chriſtian ſubiects, then that of Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, who all the time that he wandred vp and downe on earth in our fleſh, though he were very God as well as man, yet he neuer diſdained to reuerence and obey ſuch as were in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in his time, he neuer behaued himſelfe ſeditiouſtie, nor rebelliouſlie, but rather taught and commaunded, to giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which vnto him belonged; openly he taught the Iewes to pay tribute vnto the Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, openly for himſelfe and his Apoſtles he payed tribute, yea when he wanted money,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.27</note> rather then he would faile in paiments due and accuſtomed to the higher power, he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſlie cauſed a Fiſh to bring him xx. pence to diſcharge ſuch duties for himſelfe and his companie. And he himſelfe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20868:12"/>and his Apoſtles receiued many and diuerſe iniuties at the hands of wicked and faithleſſe magiſtrates, yet neither he nor any of them euer moued nor ſtirred vp any ſedition or rebellion againſt any gouernours, and ſuch as were in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but paciently without reſiſtance put vp, digeſted, and quietly ſuffered all vexations, ſlaunders, and wrongs, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the authoritie of power was inſtituted and ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, and therfore both with their words they taught obedience, and in all their doings they gaue examples of the great reckoning and account that they made of the ſame. Among many other examples of the new teſtament this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may ſuffice which our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath giuen for an eternall example to all manner of ſubiects, to teach them to yeeld this chriſtian and dutifull obedience to all Soueraigne Emperours, Kings, and Princes, yea though ſtrangers, wicked and wrongfull, if God at any time for our ſinnes ſake place ſuch ouer vs. But ſome man may here aske a queſtion and ſay, how and in what maner ſhould a ſubiect obay his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne in ſuch ſort that he may be aſſured that his obedience ſhalbe accepted before God,
<note place="margin">A queſtion concerning obedience reſolued.</note> and dutifully diſcharged before man? To whom I anſwere. A faithfull and a true hearted ſubiect muſt be carefull and heedfull to ſerue and obaye his ſoueraigne in thought, in word, or deed. A faythfull and a true hearted ſubiect muſt be watchfull and warie that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend not, that he breake not his allegia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce neither in thought neither in word, nor in deed. And firſt concerning thought: Note this,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.6.</note> that if God will haue ſeruants obedient to their maiſters in ſingleneſſe of heart, not with eie ſeruice as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſers but from the heart. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.6. how much more fit and meete is it, that ſubiects ſhould obay &amp; ſerue their ſo ueraigne with the like ſingleneſſe and ſimplicitie of heart and not with outward ſhewes only, where their hartes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre not with their outward appearances. And God is a ſpirite. <hi>Io.</hi> 4.24. and will haue himſelfe worſhipped in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in truth, ſo let no ſubiect doubt of it, but that he will likewiſe haue his owne choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deputies, his owne ſword bearers, to haue their due yeelded them from the heart,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20868:13"/>he himſelfe knoweth the imaginations of the heart and all the ſecret thoughts therein,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 28. <hi>Pron.</hi>
                  </note> he himſelfe ſayth, <hi>Da mih<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cor; Giue me thy heart.</hi> And ſhall not they whom the ſame God hath ordeyned, appoynted, and ſubſtituted to be his depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vizegerents, and miniſters, to ſupplie his roome and place among men haue and be ſerued with the verie hearts of their ſubiectes? Surely they are very vngodly men, and as the holy ghoſt calleth them the ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.27.</note> that is vnyoaked perſons, which refuſe to draw in the yoake of loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and dutiful obedience, and that euen from the very heart, which is that part of man that God moſt chiefly reſpecteth. And note this moreouer, that God in plaine and expreſſe words prohibiteth curſing of the king, yea euen in ſecret thought:
<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.20.</note> thence then wee may plainly gather and learne that as God will not haue a king to be curſed, no not ſo much as in the ſecret thought of a ſubiect, ſo no doubt on the other ſide the ſame God will haue a king to be ſerued and obayed yea euen in ſecret thought. Chriſtian, godly, wiſe, and dutifull ſubiects ought to repreſſe and ſuppreſſe in themſelues euery inſurrection in minde, and all deprauing and light account of their Soueraigns, &amp; a diſloyall thought ought not to haue any place or poſſeſſion in any corner of their hearts, for the reuerence of the king hath God ſetled and ſeated immediatly vpon the conſcience of the ſubiect, ſo that what ſubiect ſoeuer deiecteth the King out of his conſcience deiecteth God himſelfe who requireth to ſit in his conſcience, and that ſubiect which willingly, wittingly, and ſeeingly yeeldeth to entertaine in his thought an vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent eſtimation of his Soueraigne,
<note place="margin">What it is for a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and cheriſh an euill thought in his heart againſt his ſoucraigne.</note> cannot be excuſed in that very acte from deſpiſing and deſpiting of God, for though the externall ſubiection and obedience be neuer ſo great and ſtrict, yet his contemptuous thought (though the diſreuerence be neuer ſo ſecret) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſtand without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and that conſcience that is guilty of deſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and quarrelſome thoughts againſt the Lordes annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (how cloſely ſo euer it lurketh) <hi>is filthy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt. Iude. verſe</hi> 8.</note> as Saint <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20868:13"/>
               <p> And therefore as true loyall ſubiects doe tender the quiet and ſafe keeping of their owne conſciences, they muſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and carefully keepe the obedience and reuerence of their King in the reines of their thoughts, which is the very originall fountaine of all true obedience, flowing and iſſuing out firſt from the very internall thoughts of the heart.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Keepe thine heart with all diligence,</hi> ſaith the wiſedome of God by <hi>Salomon:</hi> for as the heart is eyther pure or corrupt, ſo is the whole courſe of a mans life.</p>
               <p>A man that would haue water ſweete, cleane, and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, for his meate, drinke, or any other his neceſſarie vſe, muſt be carefull to keepe the very ſpring-head cleane, cleare, and free from all poyſon and corruption: Euen ſo a good ſubiect muſt alwayes be mindefull to preſerue the thoughts of his heart pure and free from any contemptuous rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or diſloyall conceits againſt his ſupreame head, and ſo ſhall he eaſilie by ſuch cuſtodie of the heart, preſerue and keepe the purer both his wordes, and all the actions of his life, both for duties towards God and towards <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Wee finde it and prooue it too true by our deare bought experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.21.</note> and the holy-ghoſt doth teach vs the ſame in plaine termes, <hi>that the heart of man is deceitfull and wicked aboue all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O how needfull then is the counſaile of <hi>Salomon</hi> before cited, <hi>To keepe the heart with all diligence,</hi> with inward dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent keeping, and with outward diligent keeping, with inward diligent keeping, leaſt corruption ariſing from the inward thoughts of the heart, burſt out from thence to the polluting and defiling of our words and deedes in duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Soueraigne: with outward diligent keeping, leaſt from without from ouer-familiar conuerſing, and company-keepings with the ambitious, rebellious, and other wicked, diſloyall and male-contented perſons, the deuils outwarde meanes, which he vſeth to the ſeducing of good ſubiects by them, by their counſailes and entiſing perſwaſions to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, infect, and poyſon the very intrailes of the heart and ſecret thoughts.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20868:14"/>
               <p> Full wiſe, and very neceſſarie is the counſell of the Poet:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Obſta principijs ſero medicina paratur</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cum mala per longas conualuêre moras.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Quid:</note>
                     </l>
                  </q> And an other ſaith:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Stoppe the beginnings, ſo ſhalt thou be ſure,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All dangerous diſeaſes to helpe and to cure.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> If any impious, irreligious, fawning, flattering <hi>Abſolon</hi>-like natured ſubiect, with faire ſpeeches, flatterie, &amp; great promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes aſſault thy ſimple and plaine meaning heart,
<note place="margin">What is to be done when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is entiſed or drawne by any kind of meanes to yeeld to treaſon.</note> drawing by any way and meanes towards diſloyaltie, marke ſuch well and auoide them, nay not onely that, but moreouer, be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo noble, neuer ſo popular, neuer ſo welbeloued, neuer ſo mightie, nay if he were the ſonne of thine owne mother, or thine owne ſonne or thy daughter, or thy wife that lyeth in thy boſome, or thy deareſt friend which is to thee as thine owne ſoule, if any of theſe, yea if all theſe ſhould entiſe thee, allure thee, or goe about cunningly to with-drawe thee from any one iot of true and dutifull allegiance, yet keepe thou diligently thy thoughts, thy words and thy deeds, from yeelding vnto them, keepe diligently the paſſages of thy ſences ſo that they make not an entrie into thine heart, reſiſt the enemie rather without the gates, then within the walls: conſent not to any ſuch entiſers, heare them not with thine care, pittye them not with thine eye, keepe not their ſecrets in thine heart,
<note place="margin">Treaſon is not to be hid and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed for any mans ſake.</note> but diſcouer their plotting conſpiracies and trayterous patching practiſies, be he or ſhe neuer ſo neare, neuer ſo deare vnto thee: yet ſhew rather thine obedience to God, thy true loyaltie to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and thy chriſtian loue to thy Countrie, from which let not all thy friends in the world withdrawe thee, for as that good and moſt famous father of his country <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid once very wel,
<note place="margin">Cicero in Laelioſuo.</note> 
                  <hi>Nulla eſt excuſatio pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiſi amici cauſa peccaueris.</hi> It is no excuſe for thyne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, if for thy friendes ſake thou do amiſſe. Take example and learne of <hi>Mordacai</hi> who with all expedition detected the conſpiracie of <hi>Bigton</hi> and <hi>Tereſh</hi> againſt their king <hi>Aſsuerus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſter.</hi> 2.2.</note> which their treaſon ſhould haue beene put in execution the next daye at the kinges next going abroade
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20868:14"/>had not faithfull <hi>Mordacai</hi> diſcloſed the ſame, and that as ſoone as euer he knew it.
<note place="margin">Delay is dangerous eſpecially in fire and in treaſon. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 8, 3</note> Subiects in whom true allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hath taken ſure roote muſt be moſt carefull herein, yea euen in the very beginning, for in fire and treaſon. <hi>Moratra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit periculum,</hi> lingering delayes in this caſe are perilous. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally as wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> praied vnto God to turne the hearts of his people to him: ſo like a good ſubiect pray thou to thy God to conuert and turne the hearts of all ſubiects to their kings, and pray thou likewiſe to the moſt high and mighty king of kinges to direct thy heart, thy ſecret thoughts, and therewithall thy words and proceedings to the performance of all loyall obedience, and reuerent duties to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and ſee that thou breake not thine allegiance to him in thoughts, nor wordes much leſſe in open actions. So doing amonge manifold other graces, fauours, and bleſſings which ſhall follow thee &amp; ouertake thee in earth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.11. What vſe is to be made by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of bad ſubiects proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and of their end. <hi>Abſolon</hi> his example of treaſon, &amp; of his end. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.2.3.4. &amp;c. What out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes <hi>Abſolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> vſed to bring his wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. And were foure: 1. Slander. 2. Flatterie.</note> this is one promiſed to him that loueth pureneſſe of heart, that <hi>the King ſhall be thy friend, Pro. 22.11.</hi> and in heauen thy felicity ſhalbe <hi>to ſee God,</hi> by the promiſe of Chriſt Ieſus his own mouth as in <hi>Mat. 5.8.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much for the good, and imitable examples of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the beſt ſubiects, and of the maner of true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And now a while to ſpeake of ſome examples of worſſe kinde of ſubiects, of their contempt, diſobedience, conſpiracies and rebellions, againſt the higher powers, whoſe ends, bad ſucceſſe, and ſhamfull confuſions, may be warnings and caueats for all poſteritie to take heede of the like diſloyall and traiterous enterpriſes, leaſt they bring the like ends with them. And among theſe, firſt to begin with <hi>Abſolon,</hi> the worſt ſonne of the beſt father that euer we read of in theſe caſes, a double traitor; a traitor to his father, and a traitor to his King, though all againſt the onely perſon of <hi>Dauid</hi> his father, who firſt by ſlandering, ſecondly by flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, thirdly by faire promiſes, and fourthly by hypocriſie at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted moſt high treaſon. Firſt by ſlandering his fathers gouernment, as though therein were to iuſtice miniſtred, nor any body deputed to heare and determine matters in controuerſie. Secondly by flatterie, in dooing obeyſance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20868:15"/>putting forth his hand,
<note place="margin">3. Faire promiſes.</note> taking and kiſſing ſuch as came neare vnto him: Thirdly by faire promiſes, that if he were made a iudge he would do iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to euery one that ſhould haue any matter or controuerſie:
<note place="margin">4. Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</note> And fourthly by hipocriſie counterfaiting holineſſe to go to <hi>Hebron,</hi> to ſerue the Lord there by performing of a vow, and offering a peace offering, whereas in deed he meant no ſuch matter, but only in that place vnder that colour to drawe an heade of his fathers ſubiects to depoſe his father from his kingly throne, and himſelfe to vſurpe the ſame. O moſt vile, traiterous, and double vnnaturall fact: but marke the end what became of it,
<note place="margin">The end of all <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and traiterous practiſes.</note> what ſucceſſe had he, how proſpered he? <hi>Ahitophel</hi> his chiefe counſailer hanged himſelfe, twentie thouſand of his followers poore ſeduced common people were ſlaine in the field, by king <hi>Dauid</hi> his ſeruants, (God fauoring a righteous cauſe) and <hi>Abſolon</hi> himſelfe though a man of very goodly perſon, dearly beloued of his father (who for all his rebellon yet gaue commaundement to ſaue his life) and alſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely fauoured and followed of the common people, ſo that by all likelyhood, no man would or durſt lay but the weight of one finger on him, to hurt him: But yet notwithſtanding all this, God aboue the king of all kings, diſliking this rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and forbidden diſobedience againſt ſuch as he in his wiſdome ſetteth vp in authoritie, to leaue an euerlaſting memoriall, and a terrible example of his vengeance againſt all ſuch to the end of the world, did not only confound and ouerthrow all his conſpiracie, treaſon and rebellion, but alſo rather then there ſhould want a gallowes or gibbet, or an halter to truſſe vp one that had ſo wel deſerued ſuch a death; God prouided an Oake tree to ſerue that turne in ſteed of a gallowes,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.9.14.</note> as he was fleeing by the way, to hange him on by the haire of his owne head inſteed of an halter, vntill <hi>Ioab</hi> haſting to the place, with three darts thruſt him through, &amp; ſo ended him,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.22.</note> whom he founde hanging aliue, when he came firſt to him. And what better ſpeed had <hi>Sheba</hi> an other traiterous rebell againſt the ſame king <hi>Dauid,</hi> loſt he not his head? had he not his head cut from his ſhoulders, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20868:15"/>ſent for a preſent by the citizens of <hi>Abel</hi> vnto <hi>Ioah, Dauids</hi> chiefe captaine? And what ſhall I write more? It would make this my Looking-glaſſe too large and too heauie if I ſhould as fully, as of ſuch matter there is ſtore, diſplay herein the vile trecherous beginnings, the moſt horrible, enuious, malicious, ambitious, and rebellious proceedings, and the worthely deſerued ſhamfull ends of <hi>Korah,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 16. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 16. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 21.</note> Dathan</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biram,</hi> of captaine <hi>Zimbri,</hi> of <hi>Shallum</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iabeſh,</hi> of <hi>Pelah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Remaliah,</hi> of the ſeruants of king <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> that ſlue their maiſter the king. And in prophane hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of <hi>Brutus</hi> &amp; <hi>Caſſius</hi> that conſpired the death of <hi>Caeſar</hi> after whoſe death they neuer had quiet day till bloud was requited with bloud.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius.</hi>
                  </note> Of <hi>Engenius</hi> that rebelled againſt the Emperour <hi>Thcodoſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trip. hiſt. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>ca.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whoſe rebellious armie the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed and diſmaide, whereby <hi>Eugenius</hi> was in the end for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fall downe at the feete of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> where notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he was ſlaine &amp; had his rebellious head cut off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſhoulders. Of <hi>Procopius</hi> againſt the Emperour <hi>Valens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trip. hiſt. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 15.</note> of whom <hi>Procopius</hi> being taken in open fight in the field, he had for his iuſt reward his two leggs tyed to two yong trees growing neare together and bowed downe by ſtrength, which being ſodenly let riſe, rent <hi>Procopius</hi> the rebell aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. eccl.</hi> 10 <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> Of <hi>Magnenſius</hi> the rebellious tyrant againſt <hi>Conſtans</hi> the Emperour who neuer enioyed good day after his rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion till he was vtterlie deſtroyed by <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours brother. And in our Engliſh Chronicles of diuerſe Dukes, Earles, Lords, and Knights, and thouſands of their followers. And likewiſe in the Scottiſh I need not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow neither time, paper, nor inke (it being lately heretofore done by others) vpon the deſcription of the vnnaturalneſſe barbarity, and high traiterous, and viperous attempts of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Earles, Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen of late time, &amp; of many of the common inferior treacherous ſort, adhering and readie at command of the ſayd Noble men and their complices,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.16.17.</note> all of them differing far from the ſpirit of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> that man of God who was more troubled in his ſpirite (being forwarned of God of the time of his death) for a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20868:16"/>for his people then for the loſſe of his owne life, whereas theſe on the otherſide ſhewed themſelues very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, earneſt and buſie, though with daunger of the loſſe of their liues, lands, and goods, to depriue the people their neighbours, countrifolks, and friends of a moſt chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, wiſe, and learned gouernor, and to ſet all vpon ſeauen and a leauen, for the effecting and bringing to paſſe of their deuilliſh, wicked, deſperate and vnnaturall treacherous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes. But ſeeing that both ſacred and prophane hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, both Engliſh and Scottiſh Chronicles may furniſh vs, as it were with whole clowds of ſuch examples for caueats and warnings in this caſe, let all Engliſh, Scottiſh, Iriſh, and all other good king IAMES his now liuing ſubiects,
<note place="margin">Learne to take vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens falles</note> and their ſucceding poſteritie laye to their hearts, conſider, take warning, and learne to be wiſe by ſuch conſpiracies, factions, ſeditions, commotions, rebellions, lewde diſpotions, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and wicked attempts, fooliſh and raſh actions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded <hi>Ad perpetuam rei infamiam:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Faelix o nimium faelix aliena pericla</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quem cautum reddunt quemque cauere docent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>O happie are thoſe ſubiects ſure,</l>
                     <l>whom rebels harmes make ware:</l>
                     <l>Full quietly may they take reſt,</l>
                     <l>when rebels catke and care.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Full truly didſt thou write ô <hi>Ignatius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ignatius epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Magneſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</hi>
                  </note> thou good olde chriſtian and conſtant martyr of Ieſus Chriſt in the Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church, <hi>No man euer remained vnpuniſhed which lifted vp himſelfe againſt his betters, his ſuperiours, his princes:</hi> Agreeing herein with the doctrine of the holy ghoſt by S. <hi>Paul: They that reſiſt ſhall receaue to themſelues iudgment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</note> that is not only the puniſhment of iudges here in this life, but alſo the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vengeance of God in the life to come:
<note place="margin">Tvvo kind of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of treaſons.</note> For the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of diſobedience &amp; treaſon are of theſe two ſorts; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puniſhments of and by God, or puniſhments of or by man. The puniſhments of men are mediatly laid vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, rebels, &amp; traitors, by men whom God doth vſe as his rods and inſtruments againſt them to correct &amp; ſcourge them by: The puniſhments of God, are thoſe which are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20868:16"/>ſent from God immediatly, whereof there wants not many terrible, fearefull, and extraordinarie examples, as hereafter anone you ſhall more at large here of them by diuerſe their ſeuerall ſorts and kinds. The puniſhments that falls vpon ſuch trecherous offenders mediatly by man, are puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in death, puniſhments in bloud or poſteritie,
<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the death of traitors, &amp; what is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by that kind of death.</note> puniſhments in name, puniſhments in buriall, puniſhments in body, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in offices, puniſhments in howſes, lands, and goods. The puniſhment in death is by a ſpeciall appointed maner of death, not common after the common ſort of other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders deaths, but as they offend againſt no common perſon, but againſt the head of the common-wealth, ſo is their death for the moſt part by the head being taken from the reſt of the body, as in their life time they conſpired, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſought to cut off their ſupreme Soueraigne head, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo by moſt iuſt death they ſuffer <hi>Legem talionis,</hi> the Law of like for like, for affecting though very ſeldome effecting <hi>(Interueniente plerumque prounclis ſuis protectione diuina)</hi> the moſt wicked, bloudy, irreligious &amp; impious ſubuerſion, and vtter downfall of kings and princes, whom God hath ſet vp to be rulers, gouernours, and heads ouer his people.
<note place="margin">Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of traitors in bloud and poſterities.</note> The puniſhments in bloud and poſteritie, is when their children, and childrens children, their bloud, and all their poſterity through the attendor and ſhamefull fall of their traiterous parents and auncetors, are ſo ſtained and diſhonored, &amp; their ancient houſes, lands, &amp; goods ſo diſſipated &amp; ouerthrowne, that their poſterity though they ſpare with open mouths to exclaime vpon them curſſe and ban, yet they cannot chooſe but euen <hi>volentes nolentes</hi> at one time or other burſt out, &amp; to future ages bewaile and lament their aunceſtors trecherous diſloyaltie to their Princes and countrey.
<note place="margin">Puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of traitors by nature, how it is.</note> Puniſhment in name, is when the very name of rebels &amp; traitors giueth a moſt odious ſcent and ſmel throughout the whole land, and reacheth alſo vnto the ears of the inhabitants of neighbour nations, leauing euery where behind it ſo vnhappy, ſo hated, and ſo infamous, and ſo reproachful a memory, that the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors bird may ſay of his Sire and lewd progenitor;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.30</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt made our fauour to ſtinke before the inhabitants of the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20868:17"/>
               <p> Puniſhment in buriall or rather through want of buriall,
<note place="margin">Puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of traitors in buriall.</note> is when traitors bodies are diſmembred by peece-meale, and being fixed vpon the gates and walles of great cities, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the eyes and reſerued for a freſh remembrance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all men, who ſeeing their mangled and vnburied lims might learne by ſuch wofull examples to beware of the like offences.</p>
               <p>Puniſhment in bodies is by the impriſonment,
<note place="margin">Puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of traitors in body, and how.</note> by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, tortures, and rackings of thoſe bodies which in the time of their health, wealth, proſperitie &amp; libertie, they yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to become bond-ſlaues to moſt brutiſh paſſions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilliſh affections againſt God and his annointed. Finally, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in offices, houſes, lands and goods, are by forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and loſſe of houſes, lands and goods, from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, from their heires and ſeed for euer.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of puniſhments which are imemdiatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God vpon traitors,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 27.8 <hi>Num.</hi> 16. 2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 18.9.</note> rebels, and conſpiratours, are famine, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilences, leproſie, fierie ſerpents, earth opening to ſwallow vp, confederacie of vnreaſonable and ſenceleſſe creatures, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of a good conſcience, tormenting with an euill conſcience: finally caſting out of the inheritance and ſtate of the kingdome of heauen, beſides many other worldly croſſes and calamities by God himſelfe laid on the necks and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this lewde rebellious generation, for <hi>ſi ſera tamen cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vindicta Dei.</hi> Though Gods vengeance be ſlack &amp; long in comming, yet when it commeth, it lighteth on ſoundly and ſurely.</p>
               <p>Wherefore as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> wrote,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> his bridle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an end in ſinne.</note> 
                  <hi>Si quam turpem cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem in mentem tuam venire animaduertis, ſulcipe ſtatim iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij extremi ſalutarem commemorationem.</hi> If thou once percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt any filthy by-thoughts to enter into thy minde, ſtraight way call to remembrance the day of doome or laſt iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God. Euen ſo would I wiſh, that when traiterous thoughts and conceits do once ariſe and creepe into your mindes, you would often-times thinke on and dayly ſpeake of thoſe ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie and manifolde iudgements and puniſhments which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſters and rebels haue receiued, ſuffered, and beene made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20868:17"/>ſubiect vnto, through Gods ſtroake and iuſt iudgment for their diſobedience and diſloyall practiſes.</p>
               <p>Beſides thoſe things heretofore noted,
<note place="margin">An other reaſon or argument to moue to obedience.</note> to mooue and ſtirre vp men to dutifull obedience, I may alſo adde this, an other forcible argument to obedience; that if wee do but a little looke about vs and conſider we ſhall eaſily ſpie that very naturall inſtinct hath wrought, framed, and planted this obedience, awe and feare, in reaſonleſſe beaſts, fowles, &amp; fiſhes, to one or other ſuperiour in their ſeuerall kind, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong beaſts to the Lyon, among the birds to the Eagle, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong fiſhes of the ſea to the Whales, &amp; in pooles to Pikes, yea euen among the poore Bees, there is a king whom all the reſt of that companie moſt willingly accompany, wayte vppon, follow, and obay. And ſhall man only degenerate and in this poynte ſhew himſelfe inferiour and worſe then beaſts, fowles, fiſhes, yea euen then the poore little creature the Bee. But if I ſhould here ſtand vpon this poynt of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience at large, and ſet downe here all that of this matter may be ſaide or written, anſwere all obiections, and refute all aduerſaries, then ſhould this one chapter concerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> grow rather into an huge volume, or large booke, then conteine it ſelfe within the ordinarie bounds of a chapter: and therefore hauing herein as it were pointed at the grounds of this matter, with ſome few rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, examples and exhortations to teach the ignorant and to put all others in remembraunce (for that <hi>In bonis obliuioſi ſumus plerumque omnes</hi>) of this ſo neceſſary a duty to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſubiects vnto <hi>Caeſars,</hi> I will here end this firſt chapter, referring the chriſtian reader that is deſirous to learne more then is here touched and ſet downe, to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thoſe learned and painfull authors in the page be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of this preſent chapter ſet down, where he at large may be ſatiſſied out of ſuch places as they intreat of obedience for any doubts, queſtions, obiections, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, which for want of time or for any other conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are here omitted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20868:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Feare, the ſecond dutie of a loyall ſubiect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome men (though not very aduiſedly nor conſiderately) do blame and finde great fault with the affection of Feare, as a thing vnprofitable, hurtfull alſo, and not falling for, nor beſeeming a wiſe nor a valiant man; whereas it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie giuen of God to all fleſh, and is not onely profitable for the eſtate of man, but alſo expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and neceſſarie for religion,
<note place="margin">How ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a thing feare is, &amp; how profifable.</note> and for all ciuill pollicie and gouernment among men. Take away the feare of euill, and the awe of chaſtiſement, correction and puniſhment, &amp; what way ſhall there be left to rule and order vnbrideled youth, or to reſtraine the wickedneſſe and vnrulineſſe of ill diſpoſed ſubiects in any common-wealth?
<note place="margin">Oderunt peccare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li formidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne paenae.</note> Is it ſaid for naught, that the euill do feare to offend for dread of paine? Or doth the holy-ghoſt in vaine teach by his Apoſtle: <hi>In cave thou doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe then feare, for the ſworde is not carryed in vaine.</hi> To what end both in ſacred and prophane writers are the examples of ſuch written, as for their euill and naughtie liues and deeds haue fallen into great miſchefes and vtter ouer-throwes, if there ſhall be no vſe of feare in vs, by which we may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained and made the more warie, leaſt we by the like do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings fall int othe like inconueniences as they haue done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? God himſelfe as appeares in holy-writ, doth admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs and teach vs to feare the King,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> and to feare the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers, which he would neuer haue done vnleſſe that feare had beene both neceſſary and profitable for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God. How true this is, it may appeare both in <hi>Pro. 24.21. My ſonne feare the Lord and the King.</hi> And in <hi>Rom. 13.3. Princes are not to be feared for good workes, but for euill: wilt thou then be without feare of the power? do well, ſo ſhalt thou haue praiſe of the ſame. 4. For he is the miniſter of God for thy wealth, but if thou do euil, feare, &amp;c.</hi> Here hence then it may eaſily be gathered and concluded, that feare, &amp; that not without good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20868:18"/>cauſe &amp; great reaſon, may be reckoned &amp; accounted among the number of thoſe duties which all loyall ſubiects are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to yeeld &amp; giue vnto higher powers, Emperours, Kings, Princes, and other magiſtrates, and that it is comprehended within that precept of our Lord Chriſt; <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars.</hi> This feare is out of queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one of thoſe things which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and therefore to be giuen vnto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But that you may the better vnderſtand the circumſtances of this feare, and ſo become the more throughly reſolued in the duty of a true ſubiect herein; you muſt obſerue, that the ancient <hi>Grecians</hi> which for armes and arts flouriſhed moſt in thoſe dayes among other nations,
<note place="margin">Two kinds of feare.</note> haue diſtinguiſhed feare into two kindes, the one good and very neceſſarie, the other naughtie and very pernicious: this good feare ſaid they tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth men away from wicked, prohibited, &amp; diſhoneſt things,
<note place="margin">The profits of good feare.</note> and maketh them ſtaied and well aduiſed in all their actions <hi>Plutarke</hi> writing of this kinde of good feare, calleth it one of the elements or grounds of vertue,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarke</hi> his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the good feare.</note> affirming it to be moſt needfull &amp; requiſite for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who cary a mind rather to feare the practiſe of euil, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to feare the puniſhment for the ſame, becauſe the firſt which is the practiſe of euill, is the cauſe of the later, that is, of the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for euill to ſo many as wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in wickedneſſe, which neuer eſcapeth without it iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſooner or late. Therfore a prudent &amp; wel aduiſed loyall ſubiect, ought to haue this feare alwaies before his eies:
<note place="margin">Timor fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis.</note> this feare I may not vnaptly call a childly or child-like feare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is vnſeperable ioyned with true loue &amp; a reuerent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation of the thing feared. This I take to be the ſame feare which the wiſdome of God by <hi>Salomon</hi> required as due both vnto God &amp; king.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.21.</note> This is the ſame feare which the good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of wiſe king <hi>Salomon</hi> gaue vnto him, after that he had giuen ſo wiſe a ſentence and iudgment betweene the two harlots pleading for the liuing childe, where it is thus ſaid. <hi>All Iſrael heard the iudgment which the King had iudged,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 28.</note> and they feared the King, for they ſawe that the wiſedome of God was in him to doe iuſtice.</hi> In this feare, in this kinde of feare, loue, and a reuerent regarde or account, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20868:19"/>feare, do all three concurre and meet together, and that in ſuch a ioynted and vnſeperable a ſort, that you can not ſeuer them one from an other. The dutie of this filiall or child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like feare, of this good and profitable feare, is to cauſe and ſtirre vp good ſubiects to haue an eye vnto the good and ſafetie of higher powers and magiſtrats, to loue them as well as to feare them, and therewithall to account of them, eſteeme and regard them in moſt reuerent maner, alwaies being carefull and watchfull leaſt through any diſobedience or diſloyall action they ſhould offend:
<note place="margin">The nature of the good or child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like feare, explicated by two ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes.</note> euen like as the good and dutifull child is afraide to offend or incur the diſpleaſure of his good, kind, louing, and naturall parents, or as the good and louing wife is afraid to misbehaue her ſelfe either by ſaying or doing any thing that her louing and kind husband may iuſtly take offence at.
<note place="margin">The duties or effects of the good or child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like feare.</note> The duty of this good feare, is to make men both apter &amp; readier to vndertake &amp; to execute all good, godly, vertuous and laudable matters, whenſoeuer any good and iuſt occaſion ſhalbe miniſtred, &amp; alſo more ſtayed and better-aduiſed: not raſhly, wilfully, and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly to take in hand any wicked, vnlawfull, vniuſt, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, malicious, diſloyall and rebellious practiſes and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, that by the ſequile thereof may procure dammage danger, wreake, confuſion or ouerthrow of our kings rulers, gouernours, or of the common wealth, or perhapps of our ſelues, our lands, goods, and bloud for euer. If wee conferre and compare together the workings and effects of the feare of a towardly ſcholler to his ſchoolmaſter and of his good feare,
<note place="margin">What feare in the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler worketh towards his ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter: the like doth the feare of the ſubiect towards his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</note> it ſhall helpe greatly both to the better and plainer vnderſtanding hereof, and alſo it ſhall greatly auaile to ſtirre vp and induce the hearts of all circumſpect and wiſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to make more accompt of it, &amp; the more willingly to embrace it.</p>
               <p>Firſt a reuerent feare imprinted in the hart of a ſcholler to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his ſchoolmaſter, bridleth &amp; reſtraineth him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the contempt of his maſter, &amp; expelleth from him all careleſnes and negligence. Euen ſo this feare bridleth &amp; reſtrayneth a good ſubiect from all contempt, careleſneſſe, &amp; negligence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20868:19"/>of his loyall and bounden duty towards his Soueraigne Emperor. King, Prince, or any other ſubordinate magiſtrats.
<note place="margin">The firſt vſe of feare in a ſubiect,</note> Secondly the feare in the ſcholler to his maiſter cauſeth him to be the more attentiue to heare, and the more diligent to learne whatſoeuer his maiſter enioyneth him. Euen ſo this feare in the ſubiect towards his ſupreame head and his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes which alſo are the ordinance of God,
<note place="margin">The ſecond vſe of feare in a ſubiect.</note> cauſeth him to be much more willing, attentiue, &amp; diligent, to read, heare, learne and vnderſtand, the proceedings, lawes, ordinances, acts and ſtatutes of his king, that he may the better know what is there allowed or forbidden, and ſo liue in the more obedient ſubiection, and not through either ignorance or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfull obſtinateneſſe to preferre his owne will before his lawfull magiſtrates and higher gouernours will,
<note place="margin">What it is to diſobay Princes &amp; gouernors lawes.</note> or rather before Gods will: for when a ſubiect doth any thing ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly againſt the decrees, lawes &amp; ordinances, ſet forth by his naturall king and his moſt honorable counſellers, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning but agreeable to Gods lawes, then that ſubiect in ſo doing preferreth his owne will, not only before the will of the king and his counſell, as though he onely were wiſer then they all, but euen alſo before Gods will, and ſo ſinneth very dangerouſly againſt both God and man. Therefore I ſay that this good and neceſſary feare, helpeth greatly to ſtirre vp euery faithfull ſubiect heart to be contented both to learne and know, &amp; ſo conſequently to be ruled by good and wholſome politicall lawes, and ſo therby to declare his ſubiection to Gods appointed deputies and vicegerents, and therein euen to God himſelfe. But here ſome ſtubborne and fooliſh ignorant ſubiect, in whoſe garden the ſeede of this good feare was neuer ſowne,
<note place="margin">An obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> may perhaps replie and ſay vnto mee: O ſir if the king himſelfe commaunded me to do ſuch a thing, or ſuch a thing, then it would neuer grieue me to do it and obay, but now ſuch a one calleth on and would vrge me to it, not ſo good a mans childe as I am, or a baſe borne fellow worſe then my ſelfe, what ſhall I be ſubiect to ſuch a one and obay what he will? no, no; I will ſooner do, yea mary will I, I wot what firſt. To the replica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20868:20"/>of ſuch an haughty broyling ſpirited,
<note place="margin">An anſwer to an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</note> and obſtinate, ſtubborne, rebellious minded ſubiect, I reioynd after this manner: O thou man voide or ignorant of all dutifull feare belonging vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> learne and obſerue that worthy, (and in this caſe) that neceſſary <hi>Canon</hi> of God by <hi>S. Peter.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13</note> Submit thy ſelfe not onely vnto the King as to thy ſuperiour, but alſo vnto gouernours ſent of the king.</hi> And learne likewiſe of an other of Gods choſen veſſels S.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Titus.</hi> 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> not to ſwell againſt, not to threaten and crack, but rather in ſteed of that to pray, not onely for kings, but alſo for all that are ſet in authoritie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them. And learne that not only the king and ſupreame magiſtrates, but alſo that euen likewiſe ſubordinate, ſubal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and inferiour magiſtrates and officers are ordeined by ſpeciall inſtitution according to Gods will reueiled: and that although inferiour perſons haue their authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnto them but by vertue of a commiſſion out of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the reſpect of the Prince, yet ſo long as the prince ſendeth him and alloweth and confirmeth his authority, ſo long is he called and ſent from God, in reſpect of thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: thou art bound to obay for thy conſcience ſake, thou may not reſiſt for receiuing to thy ſelfe condemnation or iudgment, of what parentage, birth, or degree ſoeuer he be, yea or of carriage or behauiour otherwiſe ſoeuer he be, be he neuer ſo bad a fellow as thou takeſt him after in thine owne humerous conſtruction,
<note place="margin">Priuate ſubiects of what note ſo euer, may not controule or reſiſt magiſtrates or their officers though they be ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry bad me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> for <hi>Quid haec adte, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i hic non eſt conceſſum iudiciunt, ſi m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, habot iudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m cui in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> illo rationem reddit?</hi> What haſt thou to do or meddle to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his birth, his preferment, his parentage, or who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted thee a iudge for his other bad qualities, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behauiour. If he doe amiſſe he ſhall be ſute to haue a iudge which one day ſhall call him to an accounte of his ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard-ſhip: In the meane time none of theſe by matters nor hoate protended excuſes can diſcharge thy duty and obedience: <hi>Niſi cogeret te contra dei praeceptum quippiam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, hic obedientia reprimenda eſt &amp; dicendum eſt oportet deo plus obedire quam tibi:</hi> Alwaies prouided if he goe aboute to enforce thee by vertue or vnder colour of his office, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt Gods expreſſe commaundement
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20868:20"/>and will, here in this caſe onely art thou not bound to obay: but thou may anſwere with the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> I muſt obay God rather then you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.19.</note> here onely art thou exempted from obedience, and herein yet thou mayſt not in any wiſe draw thy ſword againſt any magiſtrate, thy ſelfe being a priuate perſon; for Chriſt himſelfe in this caſe ſaith vnto thee that which he once ſpake to <hi>Peter:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52</note> Put thy ſword vp into his ſheath, for all that take the ſword ſhall periſh with the ſword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly the feare which the ſcholler hath of his maiſter maketh him carefull to do thoſe things which are right and good, and to auoide the contrary according to his maſters appointment.
<note place="margin">The third vſe of feare in a ſubiect.</note> Euen likewiſe this aforſaid good and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſtars, frameth and faſhioneth in euery faithfull and true ſubiects heart, an carneſt deſire to obay thoſe whom God hath ſet ouer him in all good and godly things, which they command to be done, and eſchewing thoſe euil things which they haue by their lawes in any wiſe prohibited and forbidden, yea although there be no penalty at all ſet thereon.</p>
               <p>Fourthly like as the feare in a ſcholler maketh him in the ende to become learned and louing to his maiſter of whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he hath receiued both learning and good manners the effects and fruits of learning, although at the firſt he were forced thereunto with feare contrary to his owne mind, will, and froward nature.
<note place="margin">The fourth vſe of feare in a ſubiect</note> Euen ſo this good feare in a good ſubiect bringeth him into an habite of all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe vnto his magiſtrats, maketh him to be come cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and skilfull in the knowledge of a true ſubiects al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance a thing (as is aforeſaid) moſt neceſſarie for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubiect to be acquainted with:
<note place="margin">It is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid in the firſt page.</note> next the knowledge of Gods lawes, and moreover it cauſeth and worketh in euery loyall ſubiect a reciproke loue towards his King, Prince, &amp;c. in li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w and regard of the manifould and great bleſſings and benefit, which he receiueth &amp; daily &amp; howerly enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by his ſuperiours good protection and gouernment.</p>
               <p>Filtly and laſtly like as a ſchollers feare which he hath,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20868:21"/>alwayes moouing and ſtirring him vp to all dutifull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and loue of his maſter, draweth a certaine good liking, inclinatton, and kind affection, loue, and good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation from the maiſter to the ſcholler, vpon the firſt triall, and continued proofes of theſe vertues iſſuing and proceeding firſt from his reuerent feare.
<note place="margin">The fit vſe and profit of feare in a ſubiect.</note> Euen ſo experience may euery day teach euery one that will giue his mind to note and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider hereof, that this loyal ſubiects dutiful feare, after a time of triall and due taſt thereof, and of the effects and vertues thereof ariſing, will win and draw out of the hearts of the king or other ſupreme heads and magiſtrats, a certaine reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proke mutuall loue and good liking of the higher powers, towards all ſuch dutifull and louing ſubiects as ſhall turne to their great and ſingular comfort, if not to his preferment, to his exaltation, and the lifting vp of his head amongſt his brethren and felow-ſubiects. Now as for the moſt parte there is not lightly any thing ſo good, profitable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary amongſt men, but it may be corrupted, depraued and decline to the worſe part through the abuſing of the ſame; Euen ſo likewife this feare hauing all theſe before named moſt excellent quallities,
<note place="margin">Feare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie thing to be giuen to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> yet may it be abuſed.</note> fruits, and effects, yet if you looke not well vnto it, through the deuils ſuggeſting and mans naturall corruptions and infirmities, this ſo good and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a vertue may notwithſtanding be diuers waies be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: as firſt the abuſe of this feare ariſeth of the vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes therof, for as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſaying is, <hi>Omne nimium ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur in vitium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt abuſe of feare.</note> too much of any thing is faulty, then they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre a manifeſt abuſe of this feare which go ſo far forward therin that they ſtand in greater awe and feare of the power of men then of Gods power, which are throughly touched with a bodily feare of man, which if they do the worſt, can but kill the body, but God who is able to kill both body and ſoule, they feare not at all, or at the leaſtwiſe not ſo much as men. This peruerſe abuſe of feare doth Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe correct and reproue, as appeareth in <hi>Mat. 10.28. Feare ye not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule: but rather ſeare &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20868:21"/>
               <p> The ſecond abuſe of this feare is when the penall lawes ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, forfeitures,
<note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d abuſe of feare.</note> and loſſes of trifles and things of no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment nor weight in compariſon, deuiſed and ſet downe by men as for the breach of any good orders, or of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ait co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, is more feared, and greater account made of it, then of Gods ſeuere threatning &amp; curſſe for the very ſelfe ſame offence, as for example; Let either magiſtrate or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſon within his owne charge, ſet down the forſeiture but of one peny, yea though it be leſſe, disbutſed and paid to the pooremans box or any other vſe, for euery vaine oth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſarily ſworne, and that ſhall preuaile more to feare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from blaſphemous and vaine needleſſe ſwearing, then can the greeuous threatnings of God, to caſt both ſoule and body for euer from the ioyes of heauen to the torments of hell, and all for the ſelfe ſame fault and vice. Lo here a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous abuſe of feare: yea and as it is in this example ſo it holdeth likewiſe in many moe other of the like nature.</p>
               <p>The third abuſe of this feare is,
<note place="margin">The third abuſe of feare.</note> when God either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth any good thing, or forbiddeth any ill, yea and that with eyther a gracious promiſe annexed for the doing of the one, or a greeuous puniſhment for the other: And man commaundeth or forbiddeth the ſame, yet theſe things are done, or left vndone the ſooner &amp; with greater care &amp; feare of the commaunding or forbidding by ſome great men, whom the world is afraid of or honoureth and loueth, then they were for eyther the feare or loue of God: before that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch great man in the world vndertooke to deale in thoſe things. Examples good ſtore, ſuch as in the laſt ſecond a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe is ſet downe, for this third might be produced, but the caſe is ſo plaine that euery man but of meane capacity may eaſily ſee and vnderſtand it.</p>
               <p>Let this ſuffice concerning the good, profitable, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary kind of feare,
<note place="margin">Of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kinde of feare.</note> ſpoken of before in my diſtinguiſhing of feare into two kinds, and now a while to the later or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kind, which was the pernicious or naughty feare, and this the <hi>Grecians</hi> alſo expreſſe by theſe two words, to wit, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the one ſignifling <hi>trouble,</hi> the other a <hi>band,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20868:22"/>as if they would haue ſaid, that it held the ſoule wholy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and bound, they deſcribe this feare alſo to be as it were a giddines and as it were an alienation of the minde from the right ſence, making the ſoule idle, dead and voide of euery good exploit, or effect whatſoeuer. And this latter kinde of feare worketh in the wicked a feare of paine and puniſhment appointed for offending, whereby they are as it were curbed and kept backe as with a bridle, and reſtrained from preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to commit their wicked hartes, deſired villanies, and damnable purpoſes.</p>
               <p>This feare is of ſome called a ſeruile feare,
<note place="margin">Of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile feare.</note> which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neither by loue nor reuerence, nor any other vertuous qualitie, as doth the former filiall or child-like feare, but onely through an horror of punniſhment which holdeth back from practiſing miſchieuous purpoſes. Of this ſpake the Philoſopher <hi>Py hag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ras,</hi> when he ſaid, that he that is letted from doing of euill for no other reſpect, but only becauſe he would not be puniſhed, is very wicked: And yet whereas the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the before cited place biddeth to feare Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> if they do euill, becauſe the magiſtrates beare not the ſword for naught. This ſame canon for this kinde of feare is very neceſſarie for the preſeruation of humane ſocietie, for if this were not, all would runne on heapes (as they ſay) through the licentious, ſhameleſſe, and naughty diſpoſed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the wicked,
<note place="margin">The vſe &amp; profit euen of ſeruile feare in ſome ſort.</note> peruerſe ſort of people, wherewith the whole world now in theſe laſt dayes ſwarmeth. And we muſt thinke and conſider, that it is farre better that the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate wicked ones of the world ſhould through this kind of feare be brideled from the accompliſhing of their vile wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and deſires, then that they ſhould haue full libertie at their pleaſures without all feare, to put them in execution, albeit that yet they cannot be ſo holden for excuſed before God,
<note place="margin">It is not onely to feare euill, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frame euill for feare onely.</note> who requireth it at all mens hands, that both euill ſhould be auoyded, and good ſhould be done of all inwardly with heart and ſpirit, as well as outwardly for any ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ſo euer. And yet neuertheleſſe we ſee it oft tunes fall out by common experience in the world, that ſuch
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20868:22"/>kind of feare doth not alwaies ſo ſtay them from doing of euill, but that though they forbeare and hold vnder for a while, yet ſo much the more they are inwardly inflamed, and kindled with a deſire to ſatiſfie their corrupt willes, which at the length violently burſt out, and euidently then may the world ſee what miſchiefes they harboured and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly ſoſtered in their hearts a long time before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Honour, the third dutie to be performed and giuen by a loyall ſubiect to the higher powers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third dutie due vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as is to be gathered &amp; learned both by the fift commaundement (as generally all that haue written thereon, both olde and later wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue noted) and alſo by the doctrine of the two before named Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> is <hi>Honour the King.</hi> This honour due vnto Kings, Prince, Gouernouts, &amp;c. is by their ſubiects ouer whom God hath placed them many wayes to be giuen and performed. The word <hi>honour,</hi> by a figure,
<note place="margin">Honour what it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth.</note> ſignifieth all that dutie, whereby the digni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, credit, and eſtimation of all, but eſpecially of ſuperiours is or can by any meanes be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kept vntoucht or vndefaced.
<note place="margin">The acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour are diuers.</note> The actions whereof are many, and conſiſt in many points: as firſt, that ſubiects of what rank, ſort or degree ſoeuer ſhould humbly ſubmit, giue ouer themſelues, yeeld vp &amp; reſigne all their actions, wills,
<note place="margin">Of the firſt kind of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due vnto magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> &amp; affections vnto their ſuperiours, to be willingly without reſiſtance ruled &amp; guided by their commaundements, by their laws, acts, ſtatutes, ordinances, &amp; decrees: ſo they be not wicked, impious, and repugnant to Gods expreſſe will and commaundements, and of this maner of honor is at large ſpoken before in this treatiſe in the deſcribing of the firſt duty in the firſt chapter.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20868:23"/>
               <p> The ſecond action whereby this honour is to be ſhewed,
<note place="margin">Of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kinde of honour due to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</note> and wherein it conſiſteth, is in talke or ſpeach, either of them or with them; in talke or ſpeach of them, that is, that the ſubiects communication and talke of and concerning ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, rulers, and gouernours, be alwayes honorably and with reuerence towards them, that they take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that they do not diminiſh nor empaire their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or dignitie, by vnſeemely, vnreuerent, and contemptuous words, and herein alſo is included the abſtaining &amp; forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all manner of euill ſpeaking, mocking, ſcorning, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing, deriding, reuiling, curſing, or banning of ſuperiours, as things moſt vnhonorable, yea worthy of death, <hi>Exo. 21.17. Exo. 22.18. Prou. 20.17.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is to be giuen to magiſtrates in talking with them.</note> And as honour is to be giuen and exhibited to higher powers and ſtates in talking of them, ſo is it alſo in talking to and with them, as in giuing them their honorable right and iuſt titles, thereby in ſpeach to declare a due and worthy reuerence and eſtimation of them when any talke is had with or before them <hi>1. Pet. 3.6. Mark. 10.17 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.15. In letting them ſpeak before vs. <hi>Iob.</hi> 32.6.7.17</hi> in keeping a reuerent ſilence in courts and iudgment places in their preſence, vntill we be bidden ſpeake, and then not to be ſawſie or malapert in words before them.
<note place="margin">The third kind of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due vnto ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</note> 
                  <hi>Act. 24.10.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third thing, way, or meanes by which ſuperiours are to be honored, may appeare in the ſubiects behauiour and geſture in their preſence, as in bowing the knees to them, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Gen. 18.2.</hi> In ſtanding by them when they ſit downe. <hi>Gen. 18.8. Exo. 18.13.</hi> In giuing them the chiefe feats <hi>1. King. 2.19. Luk. 14.7.8.9.</hi> In reuerent riſing vp before them as they paſſe by. <hi>Leu. 19.32.</hi> In meeting them, as they come towards vs.
<note place="margin">The fourth kind of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due vnto ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</note> 
                  <hi>Gen. 18.2. 1. King. 2.19.</hi> Fourthly they are to be honored inwardly in the very ſecret mind and affection, that is, their ſubiects are to thinke honorably, louingly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently of them from their very hearts, acknowledging them to be the deputies and miniſters of God, prouided and ſent of God for their weale, and the rather to moue ſubiects more willingly and readily to yeeld them their due honour, they muſt learne, know, and conſider, that whoſoeuer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20868:23"/>the deputie, is counted thereby to honour him that appointed the deputy, and whoſoeuer deſpiſeth him whom God hath ſent, deſpiſeth therin God the ſender, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer perſwadeth himſelfe that externall honouring of his Prince is ſufficient,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20</note> though inwardly in his heart he foſter &amp; harbour a contemptuous, malicious, and rebellious thought, that man is altogether deceiued in ſuch his conceite, for that ſubiects conſcience that is guilty of diſhonorable and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome thoughts againſt his ſupreme head and gouernour (though he keepe it neuer ſo ſecret) is wreacked, and ſuch a one is giuen ouer vnto other vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcionable faults:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt. Iud.</hi> 8</note> as S. <hi>Iude</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>That they are filthy perſons that deſpiſe gouernment.</hi> And therfore as ſubiects do feare to be deliuered vp into a reprobate mind,
<note place="margin">The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c. ariſe from the heart that firſt faileth in honouring the higheſt povvers.</note> and tender the works of godlines in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, let them tenderly keepe the houourable reuerence of their Prince in their minds, inward affections, and in the reines of their conſciences: for the neglect and ſmal regarde and care hereof, hath bin the very fountaine and well-ſpring of all conſpiracies, treaſons, and open rebellions, to the ruine and vtter confuſion of thouſands. And thus farre concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the third thing due vnto <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning prayer, the fourth duty of a loyall ſubiect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S euery faithfull and loyall ſubiect is to giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> obedience, feare, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, as here before in this preſent treatiſe you haue hard it plainly laide downe &amp; prooued, ſo likewiſe for a fourth duty, are all true harted ſubiects, bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, taught and commaunded by God in his bleſſed and ſacred word to pray and call vpon him for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate, good ſucceſſe, and long continuance of kings,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>Iere.</hi> 29.7. <hi>Baru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1.11</note> princes, and all ſuch as are ſet in authority, that the ſocietie and companie of mankinde may liue quietly and peaceably
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20868:24"/>vnder them, conſidering how burthenſome crownes &amp; ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, how hard the welding of them is, and how difficult a matter it is to diſcharge them well, whether it be in reſpect of themſelues, or of their ſubiects. They muſt be prayed for, that they may haue Gods fauour and his needfull protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from all wicked, treacherous and rebellious aſſaults, both of forreine enemies and home-borne, deſperate male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, diſſembling, hypocritiſh, corner-creeping conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, they muſt be prayed for vnto the Almightie, that he would direct, guide, and lead them in ſuch wayes as are moſt acceptable to himſelfe, &amp; that he would preſerue them from all euill:
<note place="margin">What things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially are to be prayed for in the behalfe of kings, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c.</note> they muſt be prayed for that they may haue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and feare of God before their eyes, as the only marke to aime at in all their proceedings and purpoſes, and that they may be endued from aboue with the gifts of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, prudence, Iuſtice, temperance, fortitude, vpright ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, diſcreet clemencie, and an earneſt zeale of Gods glorie, Gods truth, and of the welfare of their poore ſubiects com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge.</p>
               <p>They are to be prayed for, that like as God hath deliuered and put his ſword into their hands, ſo he would take their hearts into his hands,
<note place="margin">Things to be begged by praver in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of kings, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c.</note> and ſo temper and guide them, that they may vſe his ſword according to his owne will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the cheriſhing and praiſe of their wel-doing ſubiects, but to take vengeance on them that do euill; and finally that they may ſet before their eyes, meditate and conſider well of the good and imitable examples of good, godly and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Kings, Princes, Iudges and gouernours, as of <hi>Dauid, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias, Ioſias, Moſes,</hi> and ſuch other like, vnto theſe commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in holy ſcriptures, whoſe paths they may tread, &amp; whoſe famous, godly, and zealous actes they may follow.</p>
               <p>Thus in old time God commaunded the Iewes to pray for the life of <hi>Nabuchodonazer,</hi> and for the proſperitie of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi> as in <hi>Ierem.</hi> 29.7. And in <hi>Baruch. 1.11. Pray</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for the life of Nabuchodonazer king of Babilon, &amp; for the life of</hi> Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar <hi>his ſonne, that their dayes may be on earth, as the dayes of heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20868:24"/>
               <p> Thus many yeares afterward did S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhort,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, prayers, interceſſions, and giuing of thankes be made for all men, for Kings, and for all that are in authoritie, that wee may lead a quiet and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie, for this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Sauiour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And who was that King <hi>Nabuchodorazer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What a kinde of king <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonazer</hi> vvas, for vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded prayer to be made.</note> that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſo exhorted the people to pray ſo for him and his ſonne <hi>Baltaſar?</hi> It was euen ſuch a one as had with ſword and fire ouer-runne their whole land, burned their countrie, their townes and cities, yea euen <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> it ſelfe, wherein was the holy temple of the Lord, that they truſted ſo much vnto, ſuch a one as had ſlaine their king, their nobles, their parents, children, kinſ folkes and friends, and had carryed them away captiues to <hi>Babylon,</hi> he was an Heathen king, a tyrant, a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell oppreſſour, and a bloudie murtherer of many thouſands of their nation.</p>
               <p>And who were chiefe rulers,
<note place="margin">What kinde of rulers they vvere for vvhom <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted</note> and had the ſupreame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in thoſe dayes, that the holy ſpirit of God by <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted that prayer and ſupplications ſhould be made for ſuch. Truely about that time raigned the Emperours <hi>Caligula, Clodius,</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> no Chriſtians but <hi>Pagans,</hi> and that was worſe, moſt cruell perſecutours, martyrs, and murtherers of godly profeſſed Chriſtians. And doth God himſelfe commaund, charge, and exhorte their ſubiects to pray vnto him for ſuch Emperours, Kings and Rulers, as were ſtrangers, Pagans, Heathen, Infidels, murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, tyrants, cruell oppreſſours of them, ranſackers and deſtroyers of their countrie and friends whatſoeuer: How deeplie then are good Chriſtians, and all loyall ſubiects bound continually to pray vnto God, and to praiſe God, for the bleſſed and moſt happie gouernment of godlye, zealous, and moſt Chriſtian Kings and Gouernours, and for infinite benefites and bleſſings powred vpon them by ſuch gouernement?
<note place="margin">What it is not to pray for kings, princes &amp;c.</note> Surely to fall into ſuch extreame ingratitude, and ſeeinglie, willinglie, and wittinglie, to incurre ſuch retchleſſe and profound obliuiouſneſſe of Gods
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20868:25"/>moſt bountifull bleſſings through want of prayer &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing in this caſe, what is it elſe then to commit a moſt hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and greeuous ſinne againſt God, againſt ſuch gratious gouernours, and againſt their owne countrie, againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and the common wealth, &amp; thereby to prouoke God to take away ſuch bleſſings, and to cauſe them to feele many things, that willingly they would not, and to beare burthens of griefes, that otherwiſe they ſhould not, and that worthily too: This was an exerciſe in the time of the primitiue church both highly regarded and feruently followed, their forward and prompt inclination to pray for Magiſtrates may appeare by due teſtimonie of diuerſe godly writers in thoſe dayes,
<note place="margin">In the 30. chap of his Apologie.</note> whereof let onely <hi>Tertullian</hi> at this time ſpeake for the reſt, who ſaith thus: <hi>We pray alwayes for all Emperours, deſiring God to giue them long life, a ſure raigne, a ſafe houſe, valiant armies, faithfull counſellers, honeſt ſubiects, a quiet world, and what ſoeuer elſe a man or Emperour may deſire.</hi> The king of kings for his ſonne Chriſt his ſake, graunt true Chriſtian ſubiects the like feruent zeale and willing ſpirites, to be the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, watchfull, and mindfull herein, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> may haue his due, and God his glorie, for euer and euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning tribute, taxes, ſubſidies, &amp;c. being the fifte thing due vnto Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fift among thoſe things which are due to be yeelded vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that is, to euery King,
<note place="margin">The cauſes for vvhich taxes, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedies, &amp;c. are gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and odious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the common ſubiects.</note> Prince, ciuill Magiſtrate, &amp; temporall ruler, is tribute, ſubſedies, taxes, and other ſuch like cuſtomes, a thing I know very greeuous to the eares, &amp; no leſſe odious to the hearts of a ſort of ſimple ignorant people, &amp; that partly becauſe that at ſuch paiments the poorer ſort of the comminaltie are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes forced by the richer and more able ſort (as it is <hi>Vox
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20868:25"/>populi,</hi> and would to God it were not too true) to beate the heate and burthen of the day, and to ſuſtaine the greateſt charge and paiments, whereas they that are ten times the more able, are nothing the like, for their ſubſtance ratablie ceaſed, but can eaſily inuent, deuiſe, and vſe diuers cunning ſubterfugies and ſtarting ſhifts to draw their necks out of the heauieſt part of the yoake, verifying the olde ſaying; <hi>The weaker muſt be thruſt to the wall.</hi> And partly alſo becauſe that lightly in all ages there haue euer ſtarted vp (if not in deeds, at leaſtwiſe in contumelious, ſlaunderous, vndutifull,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 5.</note> and diſloyall ſpeaches) ſome ſuch <hi>Theudaſses</hi> and <hi>Iudaſses</hi> as doctor <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſpake of in <hi>Act. 5.</hi> mutinous reformers, grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and male-contented reuolters, viperous conſpirators, &amp; routing, rioting, rebels, which vnder pretence of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good of all men, and bearing the people in hand that they ſought for, and coueted only a reformation of diſorders and a redreſſe of common-wealth matters, haue ſpoken againſt the payment of tributes, ſubſidies, and ſuch like taxes, which appertaine to kings and princes, affirming them to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and extreame poulling of the poore comminalty, and ſo haue drawne the ſilly ignorant vnconſtant ſort of people at leaſtwiſe to murmur, grudge, &amp; exclaime againſt them, if not to take armes vpon them: Yet notwithſtanding what ſoeuer can be deuiſed to be ſaid to the contrary vpon the heads or by the meanes of any ſuch lewd, wicked, male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented and inſurrectious authours, who both they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their ſeduced ſilly followers through out all ages haue come euer to a bad end. This haue I read, and this I wiſh all true loyall ſubiects to conſider of, which for my owne parte I dare not nor I cannot but with all mine heart allow of, to wit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hyperius in Rom.</hi> 13.6.</note> that <hi>Ius pendendi vectig alia apud omnes gentes fuit ſemper receptiſſimum:</hi> The law of tribute paying amongſt all nations euermore hath bin a thing moſt vſuall and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed: and vnto this in the ſame writer this reaſon is added, <hi>Recte perpendunt omnes ac fatentur, quantum &amp; quam vtile ſit humanae ſocietati magiſtratuum officium, du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ij pro ſalute hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine intermiſſione invigilant, atque hoc nomine vectigalia haud
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20868:26"/>grauatim omnes illis pendunt.</hi> All men do right well conſider, and confeſſe, how great and how profitable the office of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and magiſtrats is for the maintayning of the ſociety or felowſhip of men, whiles that they watch and take paines for the ſafety of men, and for this cauſe they pay their tributs moſt cheerefully and not grudgingly:
<note place="margin">The ſame Hyperius vpon the <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> And againe he ſaith, <hi>Hoc ſcripturae approbant, hoc leges ciuiles communi gentium omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um conſenſu recipiunt:</hi> This do the ſcriptures allowe of, (wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there of tributes paying.) This do the ciuill lawes with the common conſent of all nations accept of. And a none after he concludeth this matter of tribute paying with theſe words, <hi>Vectigalia iuxta receptiſſimum omnibus gentibus ius ſunt danda, idque pro quadam conteſtatione obedienciae magiſtratibus debitae, ob beneficia quae per coſdem in communi vita obueniunt.</hi> Tributs according to the law admitted among all nations are to be payed, and that for a certaine witneſſing of obedient magiſtrats, for the benefits which in common life befall by them.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactus</hi> and <hi>Bucer</hi> their opinions concerning tributes, taxes, &amp;c.</note> And <hi>Theophilactus</hi> an ancient, a learned, and approued authour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menting vpon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Rom. chap. 13.</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Reddite tributum</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo reddendi ſignificat debitum quod inexcuſabile ſubditis impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.</hi> And <hi>Bucer</hi> a latter writer yet of great reckoning, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and learning, agreeing with the ſame <hi>Theophilact</hi> ſaith: <hi>Non damus ſed reddimus quicquid ex officio cuiqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> damus, &amp;c.</hi> As who would ſay, ſubſidies and taxes are not gifts but debts, a gift is a thing in the free choiſe &amp; liberty of a man whether he will giue it and depart with it to an other yea or no, and if he will not giue it, yet no man hath any remedie or courſe by law, to conſtraine him to giue: but debt is a thing which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can chooſe whether he will pay it yea or no, it muſt of neceſſity be paid, the lawes will force a man to pay it, will he, nill he, &amp; of this nature are ſubſidies, taxes and ſuch like vnto Kings,
<note place="margin">The onely lawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedies, tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, &amp;c.</note> Princes, and ſupreme gouernours, debts, not gifts, due and paiable by the lawes both of God and of all nations: no with-ſtanding, no pleading to the contrary, no deniall, no excuſes will ſerue. There is no remedie for to free ſubiects from them, but only the compaſſion, pity, and bountifulneſſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20868:26"/>of the king, prince, &amp;c. in pardoning and remitting the ſame,
<note place="margin">Diuerſe cauſes wherefore tributes, ſubſedies, &amp;c are to be paid.</note> Tributes, ſubſidies, and ſuch like cuſtomes, according to the accuſtomed orders of that countrey and common wealth wherein any ſubiects do dwell, are to be paid for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe cauſes, as firſt for the maintaining and vpholding of that royall eſtate which God hath giuen to Emperours, Kings, Princes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, tributes and cuſtomes are to be paide by ſubiects for the defence and maintenance of the common wealths, in quietneſſe, peace, and ſecurity, and to the intent that they may be preſerued the better, eſpecially in time of warres,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 2. How ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie money is in the vvars</note> neceſſary prouiſion muſt be then had, and as our moſt noble king <hi>James</hi> hath very truly written, eſpecially monie is to be had in a readines, for that it is <hi>Neruus belli,</hi> without which warres cannot be borne out, and through want of it, kings and princes ſhall either be forced to yeeld vnto moſt diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and diſaduantageous peace, or lye open, both them ſelues and their ſubiects to the open rapine and outragious violence and ſpoile of forreine inuaders and bloud-thirſty enemies; ſo that their goods, wiues, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and liues ſhall be made common and commaunded by others,
<note place="margin">Cuſtomes, ſubſedies, taxes, &amp;c. are ſinewes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monvvealth ſaith <hi>Vlpia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note> and as the ſame noble and learned King cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth money <hi>Neruus belli,</hi> ſo before him <hi>Vlpian</hi> that moſt famous writer of law caſes hath called tributes and cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes <hi>Nerui reipublicae,</hi> the very ſinewes and ſtrength of the common-wealth, without which it can neither conſiſt nor be well gouerned, for according to the old ſaid ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; A great bird hath need of a great neaſt, what or who is able to reackon vp or trulie to number how many waies and vpon how many occaſions the kings mony muſt ſtill be running: little wottes, and full little conſiders the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon priuate people, what affayres their gouernours haue to vſe money in, and to exhauſt not onely their purſes but their coffers, and that <hi>Pro aris et focis,</hi> for the good, ſafety, &amp; ſafe keeping euen of them and theirs, that moſt murmure, mutter and grudge at the payments of ſuch cuſtomes, by which ſuch things cannot otherwiſe be effected.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20868:27"/>
               <p> Thirdly tributes are to be paid by loyall and faithful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,
<note place="margin">The third cauſe of paying of Tribute, Taxes, &amp;c.</note> thereby to conteſtate and acknowledge their ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Soueraigne, who for his good and royall preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation hath power to commaund them, their goods, their lands, their liues and whatſoeuer they haue, their ſoules only excepted, for that is to be reſigned only to God <hi>animam deo, corpus regi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly and laſtly, theſe tributs and taxes are to be paied by good ſubiects, yea and that with good and reuerent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to their Princes, in regard of thankfulneſſe for bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits by them and by their meanes receaued. As Dauid in his lamentation for the death of king <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.24</note> calling to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the benefits which his ſubiects had reaped by him in his life time, ſaid to the daughters of <hi>Iſrael, Weepe for Saul which clothed you in skarlet with pleaſures, and ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged ornaments of Gould vpon your apparell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20. The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits that come by a King, &amp;c.</note> And againe as the prophet <hi>Ierem.</hi> ſaid of king <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that he was the <hi>breath of their noſtrils,</hi> and that <hi>vnder his ſhadow they had beene preſerued aliue among the Heathen.</hi> Euen ſo may I ſay and write vnto all wiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete loyall ſubiects, were it not for the care, vigilancie, paines, and circumſpect gouernment of your kings, princes, &amp;c. what would become of your braue and fine attire, of your coſtly &amp; gorgious garments, of your moſt exquiſit fine linnin, of your ſilks, of your veluets, your skatlets, of your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſumptuous clothings, your ornaments of gould, your ſurpaſſing apparell,
<note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits that ſubiects re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by their king and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> and of all your pleaſures that your ſelues, your ſonnes, and your daughters do take therin. Nay more then this, what would become of the breath of your noſeſtrills, that is of your very liues, then which what can be more precious vnto you, and how were it poſſible for you to be preſerued aliue among your enemies ſo greedily on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide hunting for your landes, your goods, and all thoſe treaſurers whereof you make moſt accompt, were it not that you are ſhadowed vnder the wings of the lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted of king, princes &amp;c. vnto whom for theſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding many moe benefits receaued, and diſcommodities and miſchiefes auoyded, too many for me heare to repeate
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20868:27"/>by name, (next vnder God the primary authour of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) you are altogether beholding for theſe ſo great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which none knowes nor conſiders how great they are but ſuch as haue taffed and ſmarted for the want of them. Let ſubiects therefore be thinke themſelues in their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences how much they are bound to their ſoueraignes, and ſtudie to be thankfull againe to them, as in all other duties and obediences, ſo alſo in this point of chearfull and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling paiments of tributes, taxes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Tributes and taxes are the lawfull reuenues of Princes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caluin in his inſtitut. lib.</hi> 4 <hi>ca.</hi> 20. <hi>ſect.</hi> 13.</note> which they may chieflie employ to ſuſtaine the comon char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their office: which yet they may likewiſe vſe to their priuate royalty which is after a certaine maner conioyned with the honor of the princely ſtate that they beare. But yet alwayes ſo prouided that Kings and Princes ſhould on the otherſide haue this for their parts-ſtill in remembrance, that their exchequers, and treaſure-chambers, are not ſo much their owne priuate coafers, as the treaſuries of the whole land. Let not this doctrine that Tributes are ſo neceſſarily and ſtrictly to be payd, be an occaſion to encourage Princes to waſtfull and vnneceſſary expenſes,
<note place="margin">A leſſon neceſſarie for Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and practiſe.</note> to ryote and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue abuſe of the treaſuties, or rather the ſweat of the brows, and the very bloud of their people, which not to ſpare is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and tyrannicall vnnaturalneſſe, &amp; let them no otherwiſe thinke but that thoſe impoſitions, taxes, tributs and charges of money or prouiſion which they receiue from their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, are eſpecially to be ſupports, ſhields, and bucklers for publique neceſſity, wherwith continually without intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to burthen and weary out the poore comminalty, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially without ſome great cauſe is tyranicall extorſion.
<note place="margin">A leſſon for ſubiects to note &amp; obſerue.</note> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the otherſide let this doctrine concerning Princes be an occaſion for common people and priuate men, little acquainted with princes affaires, raſhly and ſtubornly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with iudging of condemning or cenſuring of Princes expences, although in their ſilly ſimple iudgment they exceed and offend in lauiſh exceſſe in many things, and many times <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidas.</hi> In deed ſubiects muſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20868:28"/>helpe and aide their ciuill Magiſtrates, eſpecially the higher powers, whenſoeuer occaſion and neceſſitie ſhall ſo require, yea though it were with the beſtowing of their bodies, liues and bloud, much more with the tribute of ſome ſmall por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their goods.</p>
               <p>The Saints did gather their goods in common to helpe the Magiſtrate,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bullinger</hi> in his ſecond Decade vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 5. and 6. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> ſo oft as publique ſafegarde did ſo require. The Iſiaelites of all ages did alwaies fight for their Iudges, for their Kings and other Magiſtrates, and likewiſe did all other people vpon good aduiſe taken: and on the other-ſide, ſo did the Princes for the people, ſuch hath beene the force of the reciprock and mutuall loue and dutie, ſuch hath beene the zealous and godly naturalneſſe in citties, kingdomes, &amp; common-wealths, betweene Kings, Princes, Iudges and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, and their naturall and good louing ſubiects. Taxes and tributes and other paiments of the like nature, as learned writers, and reuerend authors do teach, ate due to Magiſtrats as the hire of their labours, and as it were (as before was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi>) the ſinewes of publique tranquilitie and common-wealth, for <hi>who goeth to warfarre on his owne proper coſts,</hi> euery man liueth by that labour wherein he is occupied. The Prince taketh paines in gouerning the common-weale and preſeruing it in peace, he neglecteth his owne priuate &amp; houſehold buſineſſe whereby he ſhould liue and prouide for himſelfe and his familie, by looking and attending on his countrie affaires. It were againſt reaſon therefore but that he ſhould be maintained vpon the publique treaſure and coſt of his countrie. It is moſt requiſite alſo that kingdomes and common-wealths ſhould be ſufficiently prouided and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with money and ſubſtance to helpe in diſtreſſes, as in warres eſpecially, in famine, dearth, and other ſuch like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon calamities beſides mainteining of Miniſters of lawes and iuſtice for the iuſt gouernment and deciding of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies amongſt ſubiects, as Iudges, Sergeants, and ſuch like: and at one word, to be briefe, there is ſuch great wants of ſo many things in the well ordering of a common-wealth, that vnleſſe money be ſtill at hand in a readineſſe, there can no
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20868:28"/>kingdome nor common-weale ſtand long in any good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. They therfore that murmure, giudge, and deny &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw other to deny the paiments of tribute, go the next way to worke to ſubuert &amp; ouerthrow the common-weale, and to bring all to naught.
<note place="margin">A queſtion neceſſarie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered on and looked vnto in theſe our dayes.</note> But what ſhall we here ſay of ſuch a kind of ſubiects, as in the ſight of the world in their corne, cattle, ſheepe and other goods, are deemed worth two or three hundred pounds, yea that will not ſtick if he can here of a good purchaſe of land to giue two or three hundred pounds for a peece of land, and as much to the marriage of his daughter, and will crack that he hath an hundred pound to beſtow on his enemie at lawe, if he croſſeth his mind and will not ſuffer him to haue his wil in euery thing that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth, and yet ſo ſoone as the Kings commiſſion commeth forth for ſubſidies and taxes, this man forſooth ſtoopeth very lowe then, and wilbe worth no more at the valuation to the king then ten pound, &amp; ſore againſt his heart it is that he is tendtered ſo far: &amp; beſides this he muſt haue bearing money (as they call it in ſome countries) that is, he muſt haue of his poore neighbours each one ſomwhat to helpe him to beare out this great charge and burthen of ſubſedies, &amp; if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe he will crack them to make them ſubſedie men, to put them into the ſubſedie booke with him, and therefore they were better to beare him out, then to be brought in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to a farre greater charges then he requites at their hands. What ſhall we ſay to this kinde of men, doth this man rightly <hi>Giue to Caeſar that is Caeſars.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Maiſter <hi>H. Latimer,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of Worceſter.</note> Let a godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctor of Diuinitie, ſometimes a zealous preaching Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in England, &amp; afterwards a martyr (ſo zealous of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Gods truth, that he moſt willingly and cheerefully gaue his body to be burned at a ſtake, and his hearts bloud in miraculous manner, euen to the quenching of the fire burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lower parts of his body to be ſhed,) come forth and anſwer this ſort of ſubiects, and he will in plaine termes tell them that they are very theeues, that thus they robbe their king of his due debt that he ought to haue, and that they might with as good a conſcience take another mans gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20868:29"/>off his back, as ſo vniuſtly take and with-hold from the king that which the Parliament, the higheſt court in the land hath giuen to the King, and that it is due debt, and that vpon the perill of their ſoules they are bound to pay it. And this man of God will further tell them, that if the king ſhould require an vniuſt requeſt, yet they are bound to pay it, and not to reſiſt nor rebell againſt the King, and that the King ſhall be in perill of his ſoule for asking of an vniuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and God will in his due time reckon with him for it: but in the meane while the ſubiect muſt obay the King, and not take vpon him to iudge him: God is the Kings Iudge, and doubtleſſe will greeuouſly puniſh him if he do any thing vnrighteouſly. But the ſubiect muſt pray for his King and pay him his dutie, and diſobey him not. And know this, that whenſoeuer there is any vniuſt exaction laide vpon him, it is a plague and a puniſhment for his ſinnes, as are hunger, dearth, peſtilence, and ſuch other puniſhments of God. And vnto this ſound doctrine in this caſe ſubſcribeth alſo Doctor <hi>Martin Luther</hi> in theſe words:
<note place="margin">D. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Math.</hi> 22.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether Kings, rulers, magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and officers, vſe and exerciſe their rule and authoritie well or ill, we muſt haue regarde onely to their power and office, for their power and authoritie is good, in as much as it is ordeined and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted of God. Neither is there any cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt finde fault with power, if at any time thou be oppreſſed with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants: for whereas they abuſe the power giuen them of God, they ſhall ſurely be compelled to giue an account thereof, the abuſe of a thing doth not make that thing euill which is in it ſelfe good. A chaine of Golde is good, neither is it therefore made worſe, for that an harlot weareth it about her neck, or if one ſhould put out thine eye with it, is the fault therefore in the chaine? In like maner, the power of the Prince muſt be borne, for if he abuſe his office, he is not to be counted as no Prince, neither belongeth it to the ſubiect to reuenge or to puniſh it in him. The ſubiect muſt obay him for Gods cauſe onely, for he repreſenteth the place of God: how greeuous things ſo euer therefore Magiſtrates ſhall exact, the ſubiect for Gods cauſe muſt beare them all, and obay them, ſo farre forth as they be not contrary to Gods commandements. If they do iuſtly or vniuſtly in due time it ſhall appeare. Wherfore if thy ſubſtance,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20868:29"/>body or life, and whatſoeuer thou haſt ſhould be taken from thee by the Magiſtrate, thou maist ſay thus: I willingly yeeld them vnto you, and acknowledge you for ruler ouer me, I will obay you, but whether you vſe your power and authoritie well or ill, ſee you to that.</hi> Such as this was the doctrine of <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> cited by B. <hi>Iewell</hi> in his defence of the Apologie of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>If the Prince</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>happen to be wicked, or cruell,
<note place="margin">Defenſe of the Apolc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. pag. 18</note> or burthenous, we teach with</hi> S. Ambroſe, <hi>Arma noſtra ſunt preces &amp; Lacbrymae: Teares and prayers be our weapons.</hi> This doctrine doth our now moſt gratious Soueraigne King IAMES at large ſet downe in that his treatiſe of <hi>The true lawe of free Monarchies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beholde and ſee here now O you murmurers, grudgers, deniers, or cunning patching peece-payers of Tributes and other royall cuſtomes, in this parcell of this preſent Looking glaſſe you may beholde and ſee your right and true duties: And yet more ouer and beſides all this, heare and conſider of both the example and doctrine of the Doctor of all trueth in whoſe mouth was neuer found any guile or falſhood, Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, who when he liued here on earth, both taught as before you haue heard, <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi> And alſo for this point confirmed it by his owne acte and deed, by his owne example, that it muſt be paide, when as with his owne hand he paide tribute and cuſtome for himſelfe and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 17.</note> with that peece of money which <hi>Peter</hi> found in the fiſhes mouth. To kick againſt this therefore is to kick againſt God himſelfe, againſt both the inſtructions and example of Chriſt Ieſus, and of his bleſſed Apoſtles. And finally if you will proceede herein ſo farre as they did, in the end you are like to haue the like ſucceſſe and end as had <hi>Theudas</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas</hi> of <hi>Galilie</hi> in the dayes of the tribute, of whoſe ſhamefull fall &amp; ouerthrow, and of them that were ſeduced by them wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> both in lib. 18. and in lib. 20. of his antiquities:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 5.</note> In this world you ſhall make your ſelues the ruine of your ſelues and of your owne bloud, houſes and families, by your deſerued immature death, or els become ſubiect to great flauerie and thraull to forreiners and ſtrangers, according to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20868:30"/>Gods threatning by his Prophet <hi>Ieremie.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ierem.</hi> 28.</note> Thou haſt broken</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>yoakes of wood, but in the ſteede thereof thou ſhalt haue yoakes of Yron.</hi> And in the world to come you ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vpon your ſelues the heauie wrath of God, and ſo eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation for euer.</p>
               <p>But now here by the way,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bullinger</hi> 2. Decade 6. precept. An other notable Ieſſon for Kings, Princes, &amp;c.</note> all Magiſtrats and Princes muſt be admoniſhed to loue the people ſubiect to their charge &amp; gouernment, to beare with them bountifully, and not to nip them with immoderate exactions: which is eaſily done if they themſelues will be thriftie, and keepe themſelues mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately from ryotous gluttonie and ouer-ſumptuous pride. Let a good Prince conſider what a ſinne it is to haue his owne palace abound in riotouſneſſe and ſurfetting, while his poore ſubiects are tormented with famine and hunger. Let Magiſtrates conſider that Tributes and ſubſedies are not the priuate goods of them in authoritie, but the publique ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole common-weale, God hateth pillers and robbers, God abhorreth immoderate exactions, God curſeth polling tyrants, but bleſſeth profitable and moderate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. Both in peace and warres, agreement and concorde are much more auaileable then money vniuſtly gotten: and ſtronger is that kingdome,
<note place="margin">Of mutual loue and agreement betweene Prince and people.</note> and firmer that common-weale which is vpheld by the loue and agreement of the Prince &amp; communaltie, although the common treaſure there be very ſmall, then that countrie or citie which hath innumerable ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches heaped vp together and wrunge out of poore ſubiects entrailes, when as continuall grudge and ill will makes the Prince and people at continuall variance. And what counſell in all the world may more aptly, fitly and effectually be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and vſed in this caſe then that which our moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Soueraigne King IAMES commended to his deareſt ſonne <hi>Henrie</hi> our Prince,
<note place="margin">In his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to Prince <hi>Henry</hi> his ſonne, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> that is, that his liberality ſhould not decline to prodigality, and that aboue all he ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich himſelfe with exactions vpon his ſubiects, but thinke that the riches of his people were the beſt treaſure: and in caſe the neceſſity of warres or any other extraordinaries ſhould compel him to lift ſubſidies, yet to do it very ſeldom,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20868:30"/>employing it only to that it was ordeined for, and to vſe himſelfe in that caſe <hi>a fidus depoſitorius</hi> to his people. Thus much hitherto plainly as I could, haue I laide downe before all loyall ſubiects eyes, what is to be yeelded and giuen to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for this fift point concerning tribute, ſubſedies, taxes, and ſuch like royall cuſtomes and duties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the abſteining from taking in hand or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling with any part of the Magiſtrates office.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Emingius</hi> in his <hi>Euchiridion theologicum</hi> reckoning vp all thoſe duties which ſubiects ought to performe and obſerue towards higher powers and lawfull Magiſtrates, maketh this one among the reſt, <hi>Non irrumpers in partes officii magiſtratus,
<note place="margin">Priuate men may not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle nor take vpon them the office of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates without a lawfull calling.</note> ſed magiſtratui cognitionem deferre, ſi quid ad reipublicae ſalutem pertinere videatur:</hi> that is to ſay, It is not falling nor fit for a ſubiect to thruſt himſelfe into any part of a magiſtrates office, but to tell it to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and to make him acquainted with it if any thing ſeeme to be for the ſafety of the common-weale. For the better vnderſtanding of this duty, ſubiects muſt learne and note that all the people in a common-wealth in any king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, country, or citie may be ſorted into three ſeuerall kinds of people, and there is none but they appertaine and belong to one of thoſe three, and thoſe are firſt Emperours,
<note place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie or city, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into three ſorte.</note> Kings and Princes within their ſeuerall empires, kingdoms, and iuriſdictions: ſecondly ſubordinate or ſubalternall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats who haue and hold their commiſſions and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from the firſt: and thirdly priuate ſubiects which are to be ruled and gouerned by the firſt and ſecond ſorts of men, hauing no publike charge nor office to attend vpon but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly each of them his owne priuate buſines according as his owne place, function, and calling requireth. So then here
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20868:31"/>you ſee the difference betweene the prince, the magiſtrate, and the priuate man: Now this ſixt duty which here is to be entreated of, concerneth neither the firſt nor the ſecond kind of men, but only the third, which is the priuare man or common ſubiect without any lawfull calling to any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or office: this laſt kinde of men may not intrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues without any lawfull calling into any manner of action or office that of right belongeth vnto the lawfull magiſtrate for that is not to <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar that which is Caeſars,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take and vſurpe that which is <hi>Caeſars</hi> vnto his owne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Two things to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder this ſixt dutie of ſubiects to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </note> Vnder this duty are conteyned eſpecially two things, whereof the firſt is, that moderation which all priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought to obſerue in publique affaires, namely that they may not of their owne motion without any calling buſie themſelues in publike affaires, nor intermeddle in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment nor reformation of them, nor take vpon them raſhlie any part of the Magiſtrates office, nor attempt any publike thing. If they eſpie any fault in the common poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie that needeth amendment, they muſt not ſtirre at all ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor take to themſelues authority to redreſſe it, or once vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called to put to their helping hand, hauing their hands in that reſpect as it were bound behinde them: but they are to ſhew it to the ſuperiour, who onely hath his hands loſe to diſpoſe and order publique matters; and if the ſuperiour do then commaund them and giue them libertie and authoritie to deale therein, they may put it in execution, as being furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with publike authoritie. The ſecond thing conteined in this ſixt duty, is the caſting off, or laying away all vindic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue reſolutions,
<note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge for iniuries to whom it belongeth properly.</note> all taking vp of reuenge for a mans owne proper iniurie is here forbidden, for the reuenge for iniuries receiued, or any wrong committed againſt any priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon belongeth properly to God, who ſaith, <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay:</hi> &amp; to the Magiſtrates Gods deputies, to whome God hath committed the ſworde, not for nought, but to be Gods miniſter, to take vengeance on them that do euill, that offend by doing wrongs and iniuries to others; in this caſe then, when any priuate perſon takes vpon him to reuenge
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20868:31"/>and requite an open iniurie done to himſelfe, he giueth not vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> but by reuenging with his owne hand, he forgetteth a loyall ſubiects dutie, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth a manifeſt wrong againſt the King and his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, by vſurping their office vnto whom only the ſworde belongeth for reuenging of all iniuties committed againſt any of his people. So that to conclude in few words, this ſixt dutie of a loyall ſubiect, it is, that priuate men may not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any publique Magiſtrates office without a lawfull commiſſion or calling, neither to reforme any thing amiſſe, nor to doe any good in the common-weale, nor yet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge himſelfe againſt his aduerſarie for any receiued wrong, for vengeance is to be committed only to God and to the higher powers, to whom only it doth by right appertaine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN reading Subiect.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT is not to be doubted, nay there is nothing more ſure (good Chriſtian ſubiect) then that Sathan as he hath beene vſed to do euer of old, ſo he will ſtill hold on, and buſie himſelfe to withdraw thee from the regarde of ſome, or of euery of theſe my before handled loyall ſubiects duties, and to trumpe in thy way by caſting before thee many ſtumbling blocks, and cauſes of vndutifulneſſe, thereby to cauſe thee to forget, or elſe to neglect, and omit theſe before noted ſixe duties. Of the which cauſes of vndutifulneſſe by that our mortall and deadly foe, very much and oftentimes ſuggeſted and vrged, I haue thought it good for thy learning and warning, to giue thee heere a taſte of ſixe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this little Pamphlet following, whereby thou maieſt take a ſcantling of the reſidue, and ſo be thereby the better awaked and more excited, to beware of them all in time.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W.W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20868:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Pride, being the firſt cauſe of the vndutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse of ſubiects.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſt writers do agree and conſent, and the greateſt and moſt reaſons may be alleaged,
<note place="margin">The cauſe of the fall of Angells.</note> that the firſt and chiefeſt cauſe of the fall and vnrecouerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of ſome of Gods moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous angels, wherby they loſt their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtate and ſo became terrible and moſt ougly deuils, was pride, whereby they being but crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures began to rebell and to exalt themſelues againſt God their creator. Now the ſubtill, crafty, cozening, enuious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, being become a mortall enemie to mans welfore and bleſſed ſtate, hauing experience in himſelfe that pride was a chiefe cauſe of his owne fall, he ceaſeth not to vſe the ſame as an engine or weapon for the ouerthrowing of mortall men in this world, euen to blow them vp with pride, as it were with Gun-power, for as wee ſee it come to paſſe, when the enemies lay ſiege to win or beate downe caſtels, walles, and the ſtrongeſt holds, amongſt their batteries, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſhot, and other ſtratagems and feats of warre, they vſe this alſo as their ſureſt remedie and pollicie, to vndermine them and blowe them vp with traines of Gun-powder: Euen ſo likewiſe is it the deuiſe and pollicie of Satan, among his other traines, to attempt, aſſault, and blow vp men with pride as it were with Gun-powder.
<note place="margin">Pride wherein it conſiſteth.</note> Now this pride con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the great loue and liking of our owne ſelues, of our owne excellencie &amp; worthineſſe, &amp; a diſdainfull contempt, and deſpiſing of others in compariſon of our ſelues. A fitte inſtrument is this then for Sathan to worke with in this caſe: for as the wiſedome of God doth teach by <hi>Salomon;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 13.10.</note> Onely by pride doth man make contention:</hi> which commeth to paſſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20868:32"/>when as euery man contendeth to haue the preheminence and will not giue place vnto an other. So that that man which hath his heart once inſected and poyſoned through pride, he can in no wiſe brooke it to be at commaund, and to ſubmit himſelfe willingly (according to Gods ordinance and appoyntment) to the obedience of magiſtrates, rulers, and gouernours, be they neuer ſo well worthy of the place.
<note place="margin">Pride and hautineſſe of ſtomack in great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvhat vvork they make.</note> Herehence it oftentimes commeth to paſſe that Dukes, Earles, Lords, Knights and ſuch like being once poſſeſſed with this pride, vpon neuer ſo light occaſions, nay rather ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king offences, then tarying vntill offences be iuſtly giuen, will contenine, diſdaine, and vnreuerently and diſhonora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie vſe, yea and oftentimes alſo conſpire againſt, take vp armes, and ſeeke the life and bloud, or at leaſtwiſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Lords annointed, their ſupreme heads, ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and placed in ſuch roomes by God himſelfe: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence likewiſe it falleth out, that many priuate perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the common people will not ſtick to vilipend, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and contemptuouſly to abuſe the inferiour ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate magiſtrates, thinking themſelues in the pride of their owne hearts,
<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilles craft and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare men through pride and to bring them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie &amp; rebellion, deſcribed by a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a fiſher: blinding &amp; deceiuing the poor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fiſhes.</note> farre better men &amp; more worthy to command and rule, then to be by others (whom they thinke to be worſe men then themſelues) commaunded and ruled. It is the manner of fiſhers who vſe to take fiſh with ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding nets in running waters, that looke where they chooſe a fit place to plant their net in, there round about their net, will they firſt blunder and muddle the waters, ſo that thereby their net cannot eaſily be ſeene by the fiſh, then will they goe ſomewhat higher into the riuer and with their long poulleringe ſtaues will they beate and daſh in the ſtreame and driue downe the fiſh towardes their net, into the which the ſilly deceaued fiſh ſoone ſhooteth it ſelfe, and ſo at vnwares is inſnared, by reaſon that the net could not be ſeene, the water about it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before thickened and blundered by rayſing vp of the mudde.</p>
               <p>Euen this is the caſe of many ſubiects in the worlde,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20868:33"/>The cunning crafty deuill is the fiſher, he ſets the net of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to magiſtrates within the circuite and walke of ſuch as he meanes to catch therin, then he blindes their hearts with pride, ſo that they therewith hauing their ſenſes and reaſon darkened, ruſh forward headlong, the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them on a pace in their madde moode, into the nett, which they ſilye ſoules neuer perceiue nor conſider of till they be ſurely ſnared paſt all helpe of retyring back againe and ſo are they caſt away ere they be aware.
<note place="margin">A caueat.</note> O ſubiects, ſubiects, of what eſtate ſoeuer you be, noble or ignoble, high or low, rich or poore, looke to it in time, beware of this net, take heed of this pride the deuills owne engine: To han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle euery particuler poynt of pride would make a larger diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe then here now I purpoſe, let this ſuffice therfore for ſo much concerning pride being the firſt cauſe of vndutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as it doth or may preiudice loyall ſubiects duties to higher powers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Ambition, the ſecond cauſe of vndutifulneſſe of ſubiects.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N auncient Latine chriſtian diuine hath written,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hugo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torinus li.</hi> 1 <hi>de anima.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Pride riding in a coach, hath her coach drawen with foure horſes, the forehorſe is Ambition, the ſecond Vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, the third Contempt, and the fourth Diſobedience.</hi> Ambition therefore an attending ſeruaunt on dame Pride may I not vnaptly here ſet downe in degree next vnto <hi>Pride</hi> for the ſecond cauſe of ſubiects vndutifulnes: And this ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may well be defined to be a moſt vehement,
<note place="margin">What am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition is.</note> ſtrong, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered and an vnreaſonable deſire of glory, an inſatiable &amp; anvnbrideled greedines to rule: It is a vice of exceſſe figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting full, but againſt modeſty which is a part of temperance, for a modeſt man (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith) deſireth honor as he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20868:33"/>ought, and as becommeth him,
<note place="margin">Who is ambitious.</note> but he that deſireth otherwiſe then he ought by vnlawfull meanes is ambitious and car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed away with a perturbation of intemperance. Of ſuch as theſe there are many examples (which may ſerue to inſtruct and warne loyall ſubiects) both in ſacred and prophane hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, amongſt whom commeth here to my remembrance the notable ſtory of <hi>Korah</hi> that ſeditious headed and ambitious minded Iſralite, whoſe rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> at large ſetteth down,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 16.1.2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> with his bad ſucceſſe, and ſtrange puniſhment: In which ambitious man, (like as it commonly falleth out with all ſuch as are infected with that vice) there was firſt a male content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mind, who not contented with that honor, calling, and office wherein he was placed, raiſed vp diſquietneſſe, diſturbance and tumults among the people:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.16.17.</note> Secondly there was in him an enuious affection, whereby he diſdeined that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron</hi> ſhould haue any power ouer him. Thirdly like vnto our vile <hi>Anabaptiſtes,</hi> he went about to ſuppreſſe gouernment and magiſtracie and would haue all the people to be of equall authority, power and condition, which is the confuſion of all ſtates of people. Fourthly he rayſed vp ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſedition and rebellion among the people againſt gouernors appointed of God. Fiftly he went about to haue brought the high prieſthood from <hi>Aron</hi> vnto himſelfe although he found fault with others for the ſame. Full of the like ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humours was alſo <hi>Abſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> ſonne of king <hi>Dauid,</hi> of whome I ſurceaſe to ſpeake heere, becauſe I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed him ſomewhat at large before in the firſt chapter concerning <hi>Obedience,</hi> whither I referre the reader, and vnto the ſecond booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> where he may haue his hiſtory at the full. Let all loyall true meaning ſubiects in time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that they do not in any wiſe yeeld vnto this peſtiferous humor of ambition then the which there cannot lightly be a greater enemie to all bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duties of good ſubiects. Looke into and conſider but a while either auncient or later Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles and hiſtories and ſee where there euer was any great plagues, any ſubuerſions and ouerthrowes, of either flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing monarchies, common wealths, or cities, but they were
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20868:34"/>wrought by ambitious men, refuſing dutifull ſubmiſſion to higher powers, and deſirous to commaund and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before others. Who but ambitious men are wont to kindle and ſtir vp the fire of domeſticall diuiſions, ciuill warres, and diſſentions, making no reckoning and taking no thought what will be the iſſue of ſuch damnable enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prices, ſo they might make away to effect their owne deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed platformes. What did procure the ruine of <hi>Graecia</hi> flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in armes and ſciences? <hi>Ambition.</hi> What wrought the decay and confuſion of the common wealths of the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians</hi> and <hi>Athenians</hi> the one being maiſters of the Sea &amp; the other of the Land?
<note place="margin">The great falles and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes that ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath brought vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambition.</hi> What ſtirred vp <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey, Marius</hi> and <hi>Sylla, Octauius, Antonius</hi> &amp; <hi>Lepidius</hi> by force of armes to put their countrie to ſword and fire, and ſo moſt vnnaturally to empaire the large and great ſcope of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire? <hi>Ambition.</hi> What hath drawen ſome men to ſuch deſperate minds, ſo farre to abandon both God and all goodneſſe as to geue ouer themſelues to Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and to contract and enter into couenants with the deuill that they might come to ſoueraigne power and authority? <hi>Ambition.</hi> What cauſed <hi>Henry</hi> the fift the Emperour, by force to depriue his father from the Empire, and to keepe him in priſon till he died there? <hi>Ambition. Maufroy</hi> the prince of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> what moued him to ſtrangle his owne father <hi>Frederick</hi> the emperour, and to poyſon <hi>Conradus</hi> his owne brother? what forced <hi>Antonius</hi> ſonne to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Seuerus</hi> to ſtabbe his brother <hi>Geta</hi> with a Dagger? What cauſed <hi>Solyman</hi> king of the <hi>Turkes</hi> to ſtrangle his owne ſonne <hi>Sultan Muſtapha?</hi> What moueth many to put innocents to death that ſtand in ſtates expectant of kingdomes, that themſelues may take ſurer footing as they thinke to growe vp and continue in royall places? What is and hath beene the cauſe of theſe and many other ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicall and moſt impious and horrible actions? <hi>Ambition. Ambition,</hi> I ſay <hi>Ambition.</hi> And what ſhould I further wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry my ſelfe and weary the reader, ſpend my time, paper, and Inke to repeate the examples, effects, fruites, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quels
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20868:34"/>of this vile monſter <hi>Ambition?</hi> Let me therfore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this ſecond cauſe of ſubiects vndutifulneſſe, with my before noted requeſt, namely, that all loyall true meaning ſubiects in time beware that they do not in any wiſe yeeld vnto this peſtiferous humour of Ambition, then the which there cannot lightly be a greater enemie to all duties of good ſubiects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Enuie, the third cauſe of vndutifulneſſe of ſubiects.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third cauſe whereby Sathan vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth and maineth the good and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent conceipt of the Soueraigne in the heart of the ſubiect, is Enuie;
<note place="margin">Whence Enuie firſt ſpringeth.</note> the roote whereof is fetched out of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills owne garden, for from him came and ſprong forth the originall and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof, who in the beginning ſo enuied the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and proſperous eſtate of man, that he ſought not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſeperate him from that pleaſaunt abode in Eden, the pleaſaunteſt place on the earth, but alſo to alienate him from Gods ſauour, and by that meanes to expell him from all happineſſe, and to plunge both him and all his ofſpring into eternall miſerie.</p>
               <p>Through this enuie it is that one man grieueth at an other mans well doinge and proſperity,
<note place="margin">The fruit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Enuie.</note> whoſoeuer is once attached herewith, ſtraight-waye he murmureth and grudgeth, he chafeth, fretteth and fumeth that any man ſhould be aduaunced to any honour, dignity, office or high authoritye beſides himſelfe, inuenting, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and deuiſing which way and how to diſgrace, hurte, diſquiet, croſſe, and remooue him that ſo is preferred.</p>
               <p>The enuious man la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guiſheth &amp; pineth to ſee his neighbour
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20868:35"/>promoted and proſper, as ſaith the Poet <hi>Horace:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inuidus alterius rebus macreſcit opimis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The man that enuie doth poſſeſſe, doth pine and fall away,</l>
                     <l>At others wealth and good ſucceſſe, encreaſing euery day.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Such a waſter and conſumer is this enuie, that for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie thereof with theſe things, auncient writers both Latine and Greeke haue compared and lykened it to the
<q>
                     <l>Worme that conſumeth old ſoft timber,
<note place="margin">What things en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie is very aptly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Moaths that eate and waſt wollen cloth:</l>
                     <l>Ruſt that corrupteth and cankereth away yron.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Vipers yong ones that eate out their dammes bellies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be brought forth into the light. Theſe viperous generations of enuious creatures are likewiſe reſembled to the ſwelling toad which (as ſome report) cannot abide the ſmell of Iarmaunder, euen ſo will theſe ſwell and diſdaine at vertuous and good gouernours placed by God in the midſt of Gods garden,
<note place="margin">Other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> very well befiting the enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man.</note> to expell and chaſe away ſuch venomous toads. They are moreouer likened vnto the blind Howlet, which as it is ſayd, in the day time is very dimme and ſlowe of ſight, but in the night is moſt quick of eyeſight: Euen ſo whereas the vertues, graces, and good qualities of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, rulers, and gouernours appeare and ſhew themſelues manifeſtly to all the world in open light, as it were at the no one day, yet theſe enuious people ſee nothing nor will take any knowledge of any of thoſe good gifts, but if through the infirmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the fleſh any of them ſlippe, and be tainted with any fault be it neuer ſo little, this can they ſoone eſpie, herein they haue <hi>Lyncaeus</hi> his eies, then a little moate ſhalbe made a great mountaine, <hi>Ex humili tumulo magnum producunt olympum:</hi> If they ſee any thing well done, they grudge at it and find fault with it, like <hi>Simon</hi> the Leper who blamed <hi>Marie Magdalein</hi> for doing of a good deed. If they ſee that God accept of, bleſſe and proſper any mans doings more then theirs, ſtreight way they maligne him and enuie him, yea and maliciouſly ſeek his bloud, like as <hi>Cain</hi> did his brother <hi>Habels.</hi> If any man for the good ſeruice done for or in his countrie, be applauded vnto and haue his due honour
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20868:35"/>giuen him, they ſeeke to diſgrace him, &amp; to hold back his due from him, and to ſupplant him or keepe him vnder,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.7.</note> like king <hi>Saul</hi> who could n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> abide the ſpeach nor reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of little <hi>Dauids</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſand. If the kings highnes for ſome good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or for ſome good liking, or for ſome other ſecret pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe better knowen vnto himſelfe then to theſe men, do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norably beſtow any gift or preferment vpon any courtiers or other his good ſubiect, noble or otherwiſe, ô how theſe enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous murmurers will mutter, grudg, &amp; ſpeake againſt that, like vnto thoſe whining &amp; malecontented labourers which could not abide any equall reward to be giuen vnto their fellow la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers: &amp; like vnto that enuious,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.</note> vnkind &amp; vnnaturall bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that was angrie with his father and would not come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe although faire entreated,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.</note> and that becauſe he maligned and enuied that his father ſhould giue his yonger brother a kind and a naturall fatherlike entertainment, after his returne from going aſtrey: Euen ſo this enuious broode and ill willie kind of men, will chaunge the copy of their countenaunces, murmure, grudge, giue out hard ſpeaches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt their ſupreme Soueraigne, if he take to heart, giue ſauourable and gratious entertainment to any other then themſelues or other of their owne crue and faction whom it ſhall pleaſe them to allow and thinke well of. There is neither king nor keiſar, the higheſt magiſtrate nor the inferior ſubordinate magiſtrate, who either by birth, right, ſucceſſion, or by their vertuous and good deſert, haue beene aduaunced and exalted to any manner of honor and dignity in the common-wealth, but enuie poſſeſſing the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent heart and bitter tongues of this inſatuated crue, they will not ſtick to breake out into ſlaunderous and malitious miſreports, and to barke at the beards of thoſe to whom in al humble, reuerent, and dutifull maner they ought to ſubmit themſelues. Let all loyall ſubiects therfore take heede, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide, and ſhun from Enure this third cauſe of ſubiects vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulnes, and according to S. Paul his exhortation. <hi>Do all things without murmurings &amp; reaſonings that they may be blamles &amp; pure,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> and the ſonnes of God without rebuke in the middeſt of a naughty and crooked nation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:20868:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the lack of ſubiects wiſdome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the fourth cauſe of their vndutifulneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth way by which ſathan ſeeketh to abuſe ſubiects and to inueigle and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe them to abuſe and make leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and reckoning of higher powers and magiſtracie then they ſhould, and to grow more vntowardly and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in their bounden duties then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth dutifull ſubiects for to be,
<note place="margin">The great in conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of want of wiſdome, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> is lack of wiſdome and knowledge, for through the one, that is through lack of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſubiects become altogether vnable to iudge and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of princes pretenſes and pollicies, &amp; ſo both: aſhly &amp; fooliſhly take vpon them like <hi>Sus Mincruam</hi> to cenſure, controull and condemne the actions and proceedings of their princes, through the other, that is lack of knowledge, they be come vndutifull and diſobodient to the lawes, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, iniunctions, acts, and ſtatutes of the king and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and officers vnder whom they liue. Kings, Princes and gouernours do vſe oftentimes for diuerſe cauſes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe their purpoſes with pretenſes and colours of other matters,
<note place="margin">Princes procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies and purpoſes not to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor miſconſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> ſo that the end of their drifts and ſecret purpoſes are not right ſeene into nor vnderſtood at the firſt, this to be lawfull the word of God doth not deny.</p>
               <p>To make conſtruction of intents, and as yet vnknowen meanings of princes in any ill part falleth not for ſubiects, but rather to interpret them in the beſt maner, and take them in the beſt part. Euery creature is not acquainted with the mind of his creator, nor euery ſubiect of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour: ſo the Lord ſaith <hi>Iob, giueth not account of all his matters,</hi> and ſo in ſome reſpect it may likewiſe be ſaid of princes, that they giue not accounts of their matters to all their ſubiects.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 3.</note> King <hi>Salomon</hi> pretended to deuide the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20868:36"/>quick child betweene the two harlots and did not, what if any fooliſh buſie ſubiect or ſeruant had ſtept in to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken exception againſt <hi>Salomons</hi> commaundement of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding the infant, ſurely it had argued a fooliſh want of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſion and a ſawſie vndutifullneſſe to haue interrupted the kings attempt, wherin did lurke almoſt manifeſt reuellation of king <hi>Salomons</hi> exceeding gift of wiſdome.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Iehu</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he would ſerue <hi>Baal,</hi> much more then euer did <hi>Ahab,</hi> but he did it not, but by this ſubtilty deſtroyed all the ſeruants of <hi>Baal.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>chap.</hi> 11. <hi>de vita con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi>
                     </note> Conſtantius</hi> the Emperour pretended that as many as would offer ſacrifice vnto Idols ſhould haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to his royall perſon, dwell in his court and haue offices and great honor in the common wealth, but they that would not ſhould both be baniſhed the court and depriued pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently of ſuch honors as now they did enioy. But yet he did not ſo, but by that policie tried the true chriſtians from Idolaters, and ſo tooke to them, and caſt out the Idolaters, had it not beene great lack of wiſdome to haue interrupted theſe Chriſtian princes pretences and commaundements tending as afterward it proued to ſo good an end, had it not been buſie, folly and raſh vndutifullneſſe for any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, to haue meddled, taken exceptions againſt, excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vpon, and condemned theſe chriſtian pretenſes and pollices. Here-hence then let Chriſtian ſubiects learne to beware that they fall not into vndutifullneſſe through this lacke of wiſdome, in not diſcerning the lawfullneſſe, drift and end of princes affaires. And likewiſe let them here learne and ſtriue to be acquainted with and to know their Princes lawes, for otherwiſe they muſt needs incurre the crime of vndutifullneſſe through lacke of knowledge, for how can they obay lawes which they neuer ſawe, heard, not read of, and yet can they not be excuſed through ignorance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:20868:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning Diſcontentment of minde, the fift cauſe of ſubiests vndutifulneſse.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fift cauſe of vndutifulneſſe of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects which hindereth many from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and yeelding of thoſe bounden duties which magiſtrates may iuſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect at their hands, is diſcontentment of mind,
<note place="margin">Two ſorts of ſubiects, troubled with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of minde.</note> abounding eſpecially in two ſorts of ſubiects, firſt in the proud ambitious ſort of great men in the world, ſecondly in the wicked and wilfull needy ſort of inferiour ſubiects: of the firſt hath bin ſpoken in the firſt and ſecond chapters; for the ſecond when they haue raſhly, inconſideratly, prodigally and lewdly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and conſumed their patrimony, their landes, and goods, when all is gone and nothing left, then in their diſcontented moods, with blaſphemous and horrible oathes they will vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and maintaine diuerſe vnſeemely, vncouth, vngodly, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull &amp; diſloyall poſitions; as that this world is vneuenly dealt, that it is no ſinne to take it from theſe fat backes, and greaſie bagges that haue it and will do no good with it, but will ſuffer a good felow to ſtarue in the ſtreets, or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, before they will depart from one peny; that they hope to ſee a day ſhortly when a ſword and a dagger will do them as much good as the beſt farme, or the beſt plowe in the pariſh, that if all they haue will buie them a ſword and a dagger they hope to liue as well as the richeſt Curmuchin of them all, and that they be good fellowes, and haue had it, and muſt haue it, and will haue it, for why? as ſome of them ſay <hi>Domini eſt terra &amp; plenitudo eius,</hi> the earth is the Lords and all that therin is. Theſe prodigal) profeſſors of irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latity, in their malecontented fitts, when they ſee that their companie will ſerue them, ſtick not to deſpiſe all rules of magiſtracie, then <hi>Ex abundantia cordis es loquitur,</hi> their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20868:37"/>tongues run voluntary, wilfully, and wittingly, ſcornefully, and contemptuouſly will they caſt out words of high indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and diſdein againſt the reuerence and honor of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers: and ſo theſe wild-headed, and ſtaring eyed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, theſe impudent and audatious ſpirited madcappes, muſt be counted forſooth men of valor, of ingenious ſpirits, of manly courage and martiall natures, they looke as bigge as if their faces were made of harneſſe, and their hearts growen with haire like <hi>Leonides</hi> that moſt valiant and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious <hi>Lacedimonian.</hi> Theſe furious royſters and deſperate cauallieres, crooke in their nailes to keepe them ſharpe for a day, and with their <hi>Abſolons</hi> long locks prognoſticate ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a vindictiue reſolution of mind, or fooliſh vaine heads, or <hi>Abſolon</hi> fatal end, they want nothing but only a ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, a captaine of their owne conditions, whom they may follow, or elſe bandes and legions, of lewdlings like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues which would follow them, and then they would <hi>(Si diis placet)</hi> cut it out, for the common good of the poore comminalty, they would reforme diſorders, they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe common wealth matters, they would bridle and cut ſhort the malice of magiſtrates, the pride and oppreſſion of the nobility, and cut-throat landlords, the pilling and cooſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of lewde conſcience les lawyers, and ſtoppe the mouths of buſie controuling preaching prelates, they would deuide euerie man his ſhare, ſhare and ſhare like. But ô inſatuated, bewitched and fooliſhly inſnared poore peaſants, you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented and malitious mates, you that are ſo deſperate, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapart, rude and raſh in all your actions, you moſt lauiſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and fonde vnthrifts, you prodigall waſters, of your lands, goods and patrimony, that haue plunged your ſelues ſo farre into other mens goods, or elſe into robberies, thefts, and murthers that you can not, or dare not ſhew your faces to liue neighbourly in any good and well gouerned common wealth, that are alwaies ready to murmur, grudge, and mutinie againſt gouernment, to belye, backbite, and ſlaunder lawfull magiſtrates, to controule and cenſure the ſtate, to be factious, ſeditious and ready vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> light oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20868:38"/>rather taken then giuen either to begin or to follow and conioyne with euery conſpiracy, inſurrection, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and open rebellion: will any wiſe and dutifull loyall ſubiects think you meete men to performe that you boſt &amp; bragge of, or that which you outwardly pretend, that you can or will reforme diſorders, &amp; bring with you a common wealth to others, that haue ſhewed ſuch bad preſedents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in moſt fooliſh, needles, and waſtfull ſpoyling and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowing of your owne wealth? Are you like men to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend other mens diſordered actions, wheras your ſelues ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per abound and flow ouer with ſo many vile vices, &amp; abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable conditions.
<note place="margin">Counſaill and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for vnthrifts and waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls.</note> Ceaſe in time from theſe your vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conceits, begin the world againe, returne to better minds and meanings, take better holde, and if you haue not other callings lawfull and good for your ſelues and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth be not aſhamed of that ordinance and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of our God in the beginning of the world <hi>In ſudore vultus tui veſceris pane tuo,</hi> eate your bread in the ſweat of your faces, for a while vntill you returne to the earth, this courſe may perhaps ſeeme painfull and farre contrary to your former courſes, but it ſhall proue ioyfull afterwards for euer and euer, whereas your former deceauable courſe will fit and pleaſe your humors for a while, but yet will proue painfull afterwards for euer and euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the miſliking of due &amp; deſerued puniſhment of malefactors, the ſixt cauſe of the vndutifulneſſe of ſubiects</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here remaineth now to be ſpoken of the ſixt and laſt cauſe of the decay of reuerent affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dutifulnes towards princes, gouernours and other lawfull magiſtrates, for which I haue choſen out among many other this one, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many ill diſpoſed ſubiects are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20868:38"/>both to be admoniſhed, and reproued for it, to wit, the miſliking of due and deſerued puniſhment of malefactors, whiles that inconſiderate and euill diſpoſed perſons cry out againſt Iudges, magiſtrates, and zelous iuſticers, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and purpoſes are bent by due ſeuerity, where cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie will take no place, to amend the obſtinate wicked, thinking it better vpon well aduiſed conſideration, to cut of one putrified and rotten member in time, then to ſuffer the whole body to be loſt by long languiſhing and careles, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent looſnes of their duties. Againſt ſuch, do theſe incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible felowes, theſe beliers, and virulent exclamers on ſuch as are in authority, open their foule mouths, and that in ſuch ſort that they can do nothing by them though neuer ſo well aduiſedly and chriſtianly, but theſe buſie bawling barkers wil ſeeke either to depraue their ſufficiency, or to hinder their proceedings, or to carpe at their actions, or to murmur and mutinie at their doings, or to maligne their proſperity, or to enuy their ſtats. But ô ye wrangling crew that are ſo lauiſh in this behalfe, know you that it is the duty of Gods depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are the magiſtrates into whoſe hands God hath committed the ſword, to puniſh extraordinary wickednes with extraordinary ſeuerity, for they are taught by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> that <hi>Blewnes of the wound ſerueth to purge the euill: and the ſtripes within the bowells of the belly:</hi> For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſicuti eſt aliquando miſerecordia puniens, ita &amp; eſt crudelitas parcens:</hi> As there is a puniſhing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or mercy in puniſhing, ſo there is a ſparing cruelty or cruelty in ſparing, too much pity deſtroyeth the whole city. Euill is to be taken out of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Seeing it is euen thus, yee ſlanderous and iudging ſpirits, then ceaſe you at the length your exclamations on magiſtrats chaſtiſing offences, leaue of your prying into magiſtrates matters, maligne not their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſlaunder not (eſpecially before you throughly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) politique conueance, occupy not your tonge ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly in matters of ſtate impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto you, ſeeke not your owne reuenge on them that beare the ſworde, by diſperſing lewd lies and contumelious reproches and reports on them.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20868:39"/>And let not driue, behind their backes (in the broyling heat of your poyſonfull ſtomakes) at thoſe honorable perſonages to whom in their preſence you would bow your knees. Be not ſo forward being but priuate perſons to iudge others,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1.3.</note> leſt (as Chriſt Ieſus ſaid) you your ſelues be iudged. Be not ſo curious, or malitious, to trie out, yea oft before triall to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the faults of others, for it is the maner of wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and hipocrits, to hide their owne faults, and not to amend them, but rather to be curious to condemne and reprooue other mens, to ſee moates in their brethrens eies, and not to perceaue beames in their owne; be not ſo iniquiſitiue after great matters that be hid from you, for <hi>Dauid</hi> a man far wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and better diſpoſed then you, for he had the holy ghoſt, he would not do ſo as him plainly proteſted.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 131.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 131.</p>
               <p>Be not ſo medling with that you haue nothing to do with, for then if you ſtill on proceed the wiſdome of God by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> will pronounce you for no better but fooles. Be not euill doers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.3 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15.</note> nor buſie bodies in other mens matters, for doth not God himſelfe forbid you by S. Peter. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. Yea and finally God himſelfe by the Apoſtle giueth you this ſound &amp; fatherlie counſaile,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Refraine your tongues from euill, and your lippes that they speake no guile, eſchew euill and do good, ſeeke peace, and follow after it.</hi> In deede there is one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe for which priuate ſubiects may be tollerated to learne and ſeeke after intelligence of ſtate matters, if they may certeinly attaine vnto the knowledge of them, and that is only with a mind and an intent to direct their prayers the more certenly to God for them, but otherwiſe let not a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man make an occupation of intell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gencing and ſeeking after newes to occupy his tounge therein, for they haue other callings which concerneth them more nearly to talke of and looke vnto then that.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Tim. 1.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Vnto the King euerlaſting, immortall, inuiſible, vnto God only wife be honor and glory for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:20868:39"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
